The Accomplished Ladies Rich Closet of Rarities
Or the Ingenious Gentlewoman and Servant Maids Delightful Companion

<pb n="42 Behviour and Carving, &amp;c"/>
CHAP. VII.
<hi rend="italic">Instructions for a gentlewoman an in her Behaviour at the Table, Abroad, and at Home; with the Terms and Manner of Carving Fowl, Flesh, of Breasts and Fish, with Directions to know the choicest pieces in either, and such as are most acceptable.</hi>
<p>BEing at the Table in your due place, observe to keep your Body strait, and lean not by any means with your Elbows, nor by ravenous Gesture discover a voracious Appetite: Knaw no Bones, but cut your Meat decently with the help of your Fork; make no noise in calling for any thing you want but speak softly to those that are next, or wait to give it: nor be so dis-ingenuous as to shew your dislike of any thing that is before you, if Strangers be at the Table; especially at another's Table, eat not your Spoon meat
*so


<pb n="Behviour and Carving, &amp;c  43"/>
so hot that it makes your Eyes water, nor be seen to blow it. Complain not of a. *queazy stomach: wipe your spoon every time you dip it in the dish: if you eat Spoon-meat with others, eat not too fast, nor unseemly: neither be nice or curious at the Table by *minceing or *mimping, as if you liked not the Meat or the Company: where you see variety, yet reach not after then, but stay till you have an opportunity, and then shew an indifferency as to your choice; and if it chance to happen you have a Plate with some Piece you fancy not presented, wait your opportunity till it be taken away and changed: nor be inquisitive (for 'tis uncomely) to know what such a Fowl or such a Joynt colt, nor discourse of Bills of Fare: take not in your Wine or other Liquor too greedily, nor drink till you are out of breath, but do things with decency and order. If you are abroad at Dinner, let not your Hand be first in any Dish, nor take your place unseemly: neither be induced to Carve tho' the Mistress of the House out of Complement intreat it, unless you see a necessity for it; and where-ever you Carve keep your Fingers from *you Mouth: throw not any thing over your Shoulder, neither take or give any thing on that side where a Person of Quality, or one much above you is seated,
*nor


<pb n="44 Behviour and Carving, &amp;c"/>
nor reach your Arms over other Dishes to reach at what you like better.

<pb n="83"/>
CHAP. XII.
<hi rend="italic">The Compleat Chamber-Maids profitable Instruction as to her Behaviour in Managing of Affairs, making choice Spoon-meats, Pickling, Sawces, Washing and Starching Tiffany, Lawn, Scarfnets, Silks, Points, &amp;c. *Scowrivg Gold and Silver Lace, raking Spots out of Silk, Woollen, Linen, Stuffs, Perfuming, &amp;c.</hi>

<p>A Chamber-Maid that would be prefered, gain or continue a good Opinion, must, in the first place, be grave and respectful to those whom she serves, neat in her Habit, loving to her Fellow Servant, and affable to all, declining wanton Gestures that may render her suspected of Levity; that she keep all things in her Chamber in good Order, and have them in readiness on all occasions to take off the care of the Mistress:* Skilled likewife she must or ought to be, in buying fine Knacks, and be just in returning her Accounts: If there be no Butler, she must see all things decently managed for the Accommodation of the Guests in the Parlour and Dining-Room; and above all, have a regard to the Linnen, Plate, and other Furniture under her Command: and besides her Skill in Dressing and Attiring her Mistress, be Skilful in making Spoon-meats. Pickling
*things

<pb n="84 The Compleat Chamber-Maid, &amp;c."/>
things useful for Sawces, or Garnishing, Washing and Starching Tiffanies, Lawns, black and w bite Sarfnet, Points, and other curious Lace: As likewise she ought to be skilful at making such scowring Materials as will cleanse Silver or Gold Lace, Silver or Gold Plate, take Spots out of Linen, Silks, Stuffs, or Cloth. And because these are in a manner Secret I shall lay down Instructions for as many as are materially useful

<pb n="169"/>
THE
SECOND PART:
OR,
Appendix to the foregoing Work.

Containing Directions for <hi rend="italic">Behaviour</hi>, as to what relates to the <hi rend="italic">Female Sex</hi>, on all. Occasions, <hi rend="italic">&amp;c.</hi>
*
CHAP I
<hi rend="italic">Admonitions to young Gentlewomen, in the first place, to observe their Duty towards God.</hi>
<p>TO be enflamed with the Love of Sacred things is undoubtedly a Foundation for early Virtue to build on, and is frequently an Introduction to whatever we can justly and truly term Good or Great:* Therefore as you first owe your Duty to God who made you, and on whom depends your Being and Well being, not only here, but hereafter you must above all things, consider his Glory, and endeavour as much as in you lies, to render him tribute of Praise and Thanksgiving, imploring the Assistance of his Divine Grace, to instruct and enable you to supply your Defects, and increase your knowledge, and in so <hi rend="italic">*Remembring your Creator in the days of your Youth</hi>, That God, who loves the early Sacrifice of the Heart, will not be wanting to over-shadow you with the Wings of his Providence, and keep you from falling into those Snares Satan lays to *intrap you.</p>
*To

<pb n="172 Admonitions to young Gentlwomen."/>

<pb n="174 Instructions to young Gentlwomen."/>
thing that is necessary; for to those that <hi rend="italic">seek first the Kingdom of Heaven and its Righteousness, all other things shall be added.</hi>


*CHAP. II.
<hi rend="italic">Instructions for Young Gentlewomen in Behaving themselves dutifully towards their Parent.</hi>
<p>AS our Parents are those from whom, next God, we have our Being, and by whose tender Care and inseparable Love we are nourished and preserved from innumerable Dangers and Hazards; therefore observe,</p>
<p>In the first place, your Reverence, Love, and Obedience, is strictly required, not only by the Tyes of Nature, but by God's Holy Word, as sundry places in Scripture manifest; nor can their Infirmities in any wise absolve you, or dispense with your non-performance; but in such a case you ought to double your observance, that thereby, as much as in you lies, you may hide their Weakness and Defects from the Eyes of others.</p>
<p>You must observe at all times to obey the Will of your Parents (if it be in your power, and not contrary to God's Command) without repining, or *entring into dispute, performing what you do with cheerfulness, shewing by your willing mind your ready Obedience, and by your quick dispatch, demonstrating the Pleasure you rake in the performance, shunning all occasions of giving them any disquiet, pacifying their Anger, if it at any time arise, with submission either in Words or by Behaviour, tempering your Anions with a moderate sweetness of Disposition and Silence, for too much Ostentation or Loquacity is displeafing: When your Parents *greve be you sad; when they rejoice, be you pleasant, as sympathizing with them in Heaviness and Joy; yet
*be
<pb n="Instructions to young Gentlwomen. 175"/>
be not over inquisitive into the cause; but if you are desirous to know it, wait their leisure to reveal it, or learn it from some other Hand.</p>
<p>Forget not to pray for your Parents as often as you put your Vows to Heaven, beseeching the Almighty to shower his Blessings upon them; which is one great advance by which a Child endeavours to make his Parents restitution for their Care and Tenderness; for nothing without calling God to your assistance can in that nature be effectual; the diffarence being otherwise so vast between what has been done for you, and what you can do to deserve it.</p>
<p>Let not the hopes of Riches, no, nor the seveity of your Parents, imprint in your mind a desire of their Death, let the Almighty be offended, and shorten your Days.</p>
<p>Shun those that speak ill of your Parents and would make them seem contemptible in your Eyes: Nor let their Poverty, should you be advanced by any means to Riches or Honour, render your Duty and Obedience less, for they cannot be but the same in all condition: If they be poor, you ought to relieve them; if they are weak of Understanding, you. must assist them with your Counsel: If they be injured or oppresed, endeavour to succour and redress them; for no Years can exempt you from observing your Duty to your Parents; nor ought you to dispose of your self in Marriage, nor otherwise, without their allowance and content, your Person being indispensibly theirs in a lawful way to dispose of. And so it was under the Law of Moses in relation to a Virgin's Vow; the which, though the had made, yet if her Father approved it not, it was void; as in <hi rend="italic">Numb.</hi> chap. 3o. vet S. <hi rend="italic">But if her Father disallow her in the day that be heareth, not any of her Vows, nor her Bonds- wherewith she hath bound her Soul shall stand; and the Lord shall forgive
*her.
<pb n="176 Of Behaviour towards"/>
her, because her Father disallowed her.</hi> By this we see the great Power that Parents had over their Children, even to a degree of cancelling, and *rendring of none effect the obligation of a Vow, which Power was given by God himself.</p>
<p>Certain it is, that no poverty, fault, or unkindness of Parents, can dispense with that Duty and Obedience, which, by the Law of God and Nature, Children owe their Parents, for the tender care, labour, and cost, bestowed on them: Nay, though Parents should prove unnatural, and expose them, even in their Infancy, to a desperate Fortune of Hazard and Danger; yet still those Children are bound to perform their Duty, and look for their Reward from him who is the Author of all Blessings.</p>

*CHAP. III.
 Instructions for a young Gentlewoman at the Age of Six, or upward, how to behave her self towards her Parents, Superiours, Equals, and Inferiours, and upon sundry other occasions; as Learning,</hi> &amp;c.
<p>IN all your Undertakings, let it be observed that you are an Enemy to Sloth, not only by your early rising, but by your activity; for having neatly dressed you, or caused some other to do it, having prostrated your self before your Maker, and refreshed you with what was appointed, fall upon your Knees before your Parents, and receiving their Blessing, then hasten to School; or else betake you to such business as your Parents or Governess than appoint you at Home, doing it with chearfulness, and respect those that are over you, as well in their absence, as when present; and whether it be Reading, or any curious Work, observe that your Face and Hands are clean, and that you handle no dirty or *greasie things; neither presume to eat before those
*who

<pb n="Superiours and Equals 177"/>
who are your Instructors, whilst you at your Work or Lesson, if there be more under the same Tutorage, behave your fell kindly towards them; call no unseemly Names, nor make unseasonable Complaints; Defraud them not, nor take the least matter by force that is not your own; be courteous and mild, with a decent and winning Behaviour if your Mistress or Governess be sharp and severe, strive by your diligence to prevent displeasure or correction; and as you approach or return from her, make your Reverence, and the like to your Parents; make your Obeisance in the most becoming and obliging manner, to your Superiours and Equals: nor forget to be courteous to your Inferiours: Be sure your Tongue run not too fast, but in Discourse but moderate; Speak with deliberation, and weigh your Words before you utter them and where you are seated, observe you continue till you are called thence, or it is time to leave it. In reading upon any occasion, use not a Tone, but read distinctly, observing your Stops, that you may the better understand what you read. In Writing, beware that you blot not your Paper, but imitate your Copy in cutting your Letters fair and even; Let not your Work, of any sort, be soiled or dirty, and keep what things you use in good order, and render your Parents an Account of your improvement.</p>
<p>When you are to be at Meet, be not out of the way, but attend the Grace, and then take the place that is appointed you: After having done your Reverence, see your Napkin be *fastned about you to save your cloaths, and thankfully take what is given without craving; nor is it seemly for you to speak at the Table, unless you are asked a question, or them. Be some great occasion. Cut your Meat handsomely, and be not over desirous of Sawce, nor of another sort of Meat, before you have dispensed of
*what

<pb n="178 Of Behaviour towards"/>
what is on your Plate. Put not both your Hands to your *Month at once, nor eat too greedily: Let not your Mouth or Fingers be greasie, no more than need must; and when you are satisfied, take your Plate Or Trencher with you, or give it to those that wait, and retire, but not out of the Room till Grace is said and the Cloth taken away; at what time making your Obeisance, you may depart, unless you are desired to stay: Nor must you sit before your Parents, Governess or Superiours, unrequired, unless at your Meat, Needle, Writing, or the like; and observe. you attempt not to drink in any company till you have emptied your Mouth; and that you breath nor, nor blubber in the Cup or Pot. As for your Recreation, when leisure hours permit, let it be innocent and moderate, never *aying late abroad, above all, be Wary in the choice of your Companions and so you grow up, shun the Conversation of those that have a report of Lightness, lest they draw you into a snare, or bring a scandal causelesly upon your good Name, but chuse those whose Reputations are candid; Converse with those who are modest yet of affable; Stay not at any time, where the least occasion of Lightness and Wantonness is *administred; nor lend your Ear to Discourse tending to Lewdness.</p>
<p>For your Carriage, in the general, let it be a <hi rend="italic">Medium,</hi>, not expressing too much reservedness, which by some, is interpreted Pride; nor too much Freedom on Familiarity, which, on the other hand, will be looked upon for Fondness. Be no Makebate between your. Parents and their Servants; nor at any time tell a Lye to excuse a Fault, to keep you from the hand of Correction. Go to Bed in due Season, without any Noise, and never be seen in unseemly Laughter; nor in pointing, or nodding, especially in Company or  in places of Divine Worship: Ho-
*nour

<pb n="Governess and Servants &amp;c 179"/>
nour Age, and pity those that are distressed; Speak not at any time scornfully, or in a taunting way, but be courteous to all; and in so doing you will gain a good Repute.</p>

*CHAP. IV.
<hi rend="italic">Instructions for a Young Gentlewoman how to behave her self towards her Governess and Servants, &amp;c.</hi>
<p>AS for your Governess, if discreetly chosen, she must be a Woman of Gravity and Discretion, learned in curious Arts, such as you are desirous to improve; and although her Age render her reserved, yet must you not censure her as rigid, but comply with her lawful Commands; and by your Mildness and Industry move her to Gentleness, refraining to make Complaints, especially unjust ones; for in disapproving of her, whom your Parents set over you, you tax them with Imbecility in chusing, and by that Complaint will either incur their Displeasure, or, by removing your Governess, perhaps procure a worse; which causing undoubted, a second Complaint, will possess your Parents with a jealousie of your untractableness and ill disposition.</p>
<p>Some there are that covet to be under a young Governess, with whom they may have the more familiar Conversation, though to their small Advantage; for it is somewhat improbable that a Person, who cannot perhaps Govern her own youthful Fancies, should discharge so great a Trust as she ought: However, consider with your self that in being conformable to her, you obey your Parents, who thought fit to commit you to her Charge; and that if you do otherwise, you disobey God, in abusing or slighting, their Care and Indulgence, who study your Advantage.</p>
*To
<pb n="180 Of Behaviour in General "/>
<p>To the Servants you must be courteous and affable, but not over-familiar, lest it beget Contempt. Tell no Tales of them to your Parents, but rather strive to hide their Failings, unless they be such as are prejudicial or unseemly; and do them what good you can. If at any tine you find occasion to reprove them, let your Reproofs be rather Admonishment than Reproaches: Be not Peevish nor Froward in your Dressing, or in any other Office done you by the Maid, that more immediately attends you, but by gentle Words let her know her Error, that she may amend it; which Method will oblige and command a constant Diligence, which otherwise would be but Eye-Service. If your Parents be angry with their Servants, do you become their Mediator. Turn not your Face from the Poor; but if it be in your Power, without offending your Parents, relieve them; or as you see occasion, petition on their behalf; by which demeanour you will command Love and Reverence, and gain the Character of an humble Spirit: In which you may rest satisfied, that it is better to be Good than Great; and that Humility forcibly commands Love and Service, when Pride, on the contrary, begets Hatred and Contempt. If Heaven has endowed you with a large Fortune, and a noble Birth, let your Virtues shine with the greater Lustre; and above all things, give God the Praise, and use what you have to his Glory, and your own Comfort.</p>

*CHAP. V.
<hi rend="italic">Instructions for Young Gentlewomen how to behave themselves in all Societies, upon sundry Occasionns.</hi>
<p>First, to qualifie your self to understand the modish and courtly Expressions, it is convenient that you learn the <hi rend="italic">Latin</hi>, <hi rend="italic">French</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Italian</hi> Tongues,
*not
<pb n="Of Behaviour in General 181"/>
not only by Rote, but by Rule and Grammar, the better to understand them, since the most refined <hi rend="italic">English</hi> has borrowed from these Languages, and without this Knowledge you will be at a lots to understand those that utter high Phrases in the Court-air, as they term it; nor must you be ignorant in Singing, Dancing, and Playing upon Musick suitable to your Sex; though in Exercising your self herein, you must be very modest and moderate, your Words few, yet to the purpose; Discretion, Silence, and Modesty, being the Ornaments of the Sex. And as Society is that which all Creatures naturally covet; so, if it be well chosen and managed, it is recreatory to the Body and Mind but as bad Society is worse than none, so is it to be avoided.</p>
<p>Wherefore be not easily won to enter into Discourse with those you know not, unless urgent Business require it, lest you be suspected of Levity and Indiscretion. Always observe to consort your self with your Betters, or Equals, knowing them to be virtuous; and avoid too much familiarity with Inferiours, unless you find them very discreet, lest you fall into contempt, if Female: or if Male, lest you give them encouragement to make their Addresses of Courtship, and by subtil ways to insinuate themselves into your good liking; for Love, that takes the Diadem from Queens, is blind: and Passion distinguishes not Servility from Greatness; by which means, though you are high in Birth and Fortune, you may be brought to a yielding, which may turn to the grief of your Parents, or perhaps to their and your own Disgrace. And in this case presume not too much upon your own Strength, by interchanging Gloves, Rings, Ribbons, or such things, which you may term Trifles, left by this kind of familiarity, Love by infallible ways opens a Passage to your heart.</p>
*Be

<pb n="182 Instructions to young Gentlewomen"/>
Be not over-desirous of being seen often, in places of resort, lest you expose your self to the Aysault of the Tempter, and purchase that Curiosity with the lots of your Honour, by giving Licentious Amorists Liberty to meet you in your Walks, and by powerful Persuasions to linen to their <hi rend="italic">Syrens</hi> Charms, whilst you are no longer capable of mastering your Affections: Nor trust too much to Female Confident, lest for their own Advantage, they persuade you to a yielding.</p>
<p>As for your Dress, let it be neat, but not gaudy, for Vertue is comely in any Dress and be content to appear in your native Beauty: Let your Dressing time be short, and your Recreation moderate: In your Speech or Behaviour shun all Affetation; and be not over-fond of new Fashions.</p>

CHAP. VI.
<hi rend="italic">Instructions for a Young Gentlewoman to Manage her Gate and Gesture; to Govern her Eyes and Tongue, &amp;c. upon sundry necessary Occasions.</hi>
<p>IN this case observe that you walk not carelessly or lightly, shouldering, as it were, your Companions, nor .strutting or jutting in a proud manner; Keep in your walk your Head steady, your Countenance not too much elevated, nor dejected; keep your Arms likewise steady, and throw them not about as if you were flying: Let your Feet rather incline a little more inward than outward, lest you be censured Splay-footed; for by the motion of the Body, the thoughts of the Mind may be discovered: as whether the Party be of loose or proud *Behavour, or humble and complacent. Do not run or go extream fast in places of Concourse, unless great occasion require it; for in such Violent motions it is not always in your power to keep your Body steady; nay, by
*too
<pb n="Of Behaviour in General 183"/>
too much hast you may chance to fall and expose to view what you would conceal. And as the gesture of the Body is seemly and commendable, so is the Management or Government of the Eye; in which many things are to be observed, and chiefly these.</p>
<p>Keep your Eyes within compass; that is-letthem not be too much fixed upon idle and vain objects, nor drawn away by unfeemly fights; roll them not about in a - car elefsr and Iafcivious manner ; nor flare Men in the Face as if yeu.a ere looking Babies ; Send not private Glances; or, look, as they call it, with half a Face, turning your Head, as it-were, afide : Look not at any time over your Shoulder, if you have opportunity to turn your -felt- Open not your Eyes too wide, thereby to diftort your Countenance ; nor keep them in a manner half flint. Wink not too often, nor call your Eyes afcant; as if you fquinted ; neither .keep them too referv'd ; nor fcornfully turn them away when any Object offers. Look not too ntuch downward ; . nor with a more than ordinary Elevation. Gaze not often againf the Sun, nor on the Fire, both of . them impair the Lunre of the Eyes. 'when you difeourfe with a woman, look her in the Face with as much compofednefs a: you can : but if with a Man, to look a little downward. ; for modefly is commendable: But, above all things, as often as opportunity will pei mil, lift up your Eyes to your Redeemer, and , with holy Devid, implore him to tsae therm away from vanity: For the Eyes be. ing the Windows of the Soul; lets in Good or Evil; according as it fixes,or is intent upon good or bad Obi
leas, therefore chufe the former, and refufe the latter Let all your Difcourfys be to the purpofe, and fut. _	I _ t.__L A ,	
Z 84 Per fuafions to Modefly in Apf 1ire1. .
done on fit occafion and in feafon be fare not to Congratulate Perfons , when you lhould Con-dote them; ufe in your utterance no Hems nor Stammerings ; Sputter not as. you (peak, nor (peak many Sentences between breathings ; ufe norTauto
fogies or affeEted words - or lifpings; neither fpcak with a Tone. Decline to (peak much before Gravity, and multitude of yeat<s., unlefs urgent occafion re-quire it : and beware that you (peak not, when you are bidden to hold your Tongue; for indeed Womens difcourfe lhould not be much, becaufe Modefly and Moderation is her Ornament, and are in themf fires a moving Rhetorick. And when you have opportunity of difcourfe, let it not tafte of-Confidence, AfreElation or Conceitednefs, nor border upon Obfcenity.
CHAP. VI[.
Diret`lions for a Touttg Gentlewoman hew /lie ought to be
Peen in her Habit or .Apparel ; and what Garb i1 molt commendable, and otherwife, according to the .ality of the Wearer.
T matters not, of what Stuffs or Silks your Clo-
things . are made, fo they be decent and civil; neither by their ridiculoufnefs difcovering the Wearer fiolit and llovenly ; nor by their gaudy and carekfs putting on, to render her fufpeaed of loofe or light behaviour, or at leaftwife fubjeEt her to the cen= . Pure of • the Tj;norant. Apparel may be rich, -and-yet decent, and indeed -whether, it be rich or not, if decent, the matter is not great ; though, in this cafe, I leave it to the difcretion of young Gentlewomen or thofe that provide them Apparel, to let it be fuitable to their Quality or Fortune, and will not be of the Morofe and Cynical temper of Tome, who either believe, or fpitefully give it as their opinion , that
1 gorgeous or glittering Apparel is the Attire of Sin, and faits with the Pride of the Wearers heart ; but
Ile	_.	
PerfriafionJ to Modell), in Apparel. 18 5
I am perfuaded that the Quality of the Perfon extenuates the Quality thereof, and renders that opi-. r,ion vain and frivolous.
I mull confefs, there is a kind of Privilege in youth to go \ay ; which, fhould I too feverely reprove t might justly merit your difpleafure ; yet that Gaity may as well be in Decency as otherwife, the ufe of Apparel being to dignifie the Wearer : Nor does a vertuous Demeanour more lively appear than in Look, Speech,. Gefture and Habit, within the compafs of Modefty, though Diamonds, Gold, and other precious things, were made for ufe ; and without .being.. imployed, would be ineffc&ual : Therefore to wear them in my Opinion, is one of the chiefeft Ends for which Nature produced thena, or Art brought i hem
to a fuller perfeEtion. The Pride in this cafe being } only centered in the Mind, and not in the External Ornaments ; which is rather known by the Carriage and Deportment of the Wearer, than by the Gar. 1 ments. And' though to diva Novelty, and run into every Faihion, be not commendable, yet Moderation is not emirs ; for two Reafous : As first, tbould you always keep in a Faihion, though decent, it would be looked upon as a conceited angularity ; or to continue in any ftrange Garb, after the Fashion is altered, would appear ridiculous, and caufe Laughter, efpecially among11 the ruder fort ; as much as a Wo. man of Fourfcore to be habited in the Garb of a Gentlewoman of Sixteen ; or to fee a Dairy Maid in her Ladies attire : Therefore whatever you wear, let it he proportionable to your Body, and fuitablc to your degree.
C11AP,
T 92	Of BPhrviour l`o,Servanta,
thofe are the indearing pledges of Connubial Lo that more nearly cement the Hearts of Man a Wife, and are the Sum of their Earthly Felicity.
11
,.~_	~_	.r.,~..
rj
CHAP. XIi.
J;	fnftru&Iions for a Gentlewoman Married, how fhe ought
rr,	carry her fell towards her Servants, and in the ord
If
ing her Houfbold Afairs, 8cc.
Ci
it /\ S a Gentlewoman care, next to that of her Hi ,("+L band and Children, ought to be in the We government of her domeftick Affairs, that cann
',r	confequentlY .be done without a due regard in h
~
r proper Perron, the ill conveniency of too much co fidence in fecond Management, being too frequent apparent : And this muff be done, betides what yi fet your helping-band to, by intpef}ing the A4io of your Servants, and by behaving your felf towar
11		their as you ought, that your good Example may 1,their Guide. ~`	In this cafe, and any other, avoid Paffion, and I
!		not Rixarious, for either of there ill become a Ge
tlewoman ; your main bufinefs. with your Servan
it being to fee they do what- Is fitting, and that tilt lavifh not out, `nor war} that wherewith you intru then ; for this being neglected, the fault: wi11 I charged upon your fell.

