<pb n="4"/>
<hi rend="italic">

<pb n="1"/>
THE FREEDOM OF THE Fair Sex ASSERTED
Madam!
<p>Your Commands can never Fail to Oblige barely by being Yours that Indearing and they desire such Charms from their Original.  You Trust not howe-* these borrow'd Beauties but Endow them with intrinsick Excellence; like First Principles, they are Embrac'd as soon as Propos'd for the Reason of them is self Evident.</p>
<p>One would Contemplate the Ladies methinks, of meer Choice and *****so Divine Subject; especially, Madam! who
*has
<pb n="2"/>
has the Advantage of Knowing You, and can thereby inrich his Mind with so bright a Train of Ideas. But when moreover, You Require it, Will not the very Stones Obey!	Will not Matter itself dissolve into Meditation!</p>
<p>I am a wonderful * my Self, of the greatness of your Power; that never Thought in my Life, but upon your *Account; and *never Thought of any thing beside You, but at your Command; even what I am now doing for its Birth, acknowledges your Authority; and for its Success upon your influence.</p>
<p>Of all the Parts of the Creation that are * either through Ignorance or Humour, none suffer so notoriously as the Ladies; and the Reason is because the same degree of Contempt, consider'd absolutely and in it self is ----* aggravated always...*what has no...*great One.</p>
<p>*Not clear
*Raillery
<pb n="3"/>
Raillery, or by more Serious and Settl'd Invectives: And accordingly 'tis pursu'd by Two sorts of Men. Those who take up with the former, are such as Behave riot upon Principle with Sobriety, but give only a Loose to Censure, and Detraction, without any manner of inward Prejudice or Dislike. Nay, so far are they from that, as to admire at least, if not Adore, the Party they so much Decry; which nevertheless they do, to present a Taste Forsooth of their great Wit, and give an agreeable Relish to Conversation.  'Tis their Business to Interpret every thing in the worst Sense it will bear;  and if it will not admit an ill Construction, yet they scruple not to make it Nonsense, choosing rather to Discover their Hypocrisy, than Conceal their Folly.  Thus with them, all that becoming Conduct and mutual Respect, observ'd among the Ladies, is meer Emptiness and Formality; a little Freedom of Talk with our Sex, is down-right Impudence.  Innocence of Behaviour is all Trick and Design, and Modesty no more than Affectation. In short, as every Vertue has its Counterfeit, so every Woman that appears virtuous, has nothing of it, they suppose, besides the Appearance. This Practice looks abominable, at first sight, and carries *Guilt in its very Countenance. 'Tis a plain Composition of Hypocrisy and Vanity; and there is no third Ingredient can possibly make the whole more Odious than it is. As for those who engage in such a Conversation as this, they can have no Hopes
*to
<pb n="4"/>
to be sure of finding Favour at the Ladies Hands. (and that's a lamentable kind of Despair indeed) And for what is Future, they must be left with a Company of Pagans to the meer Mercy of Heaven. Nor will this look Extravagant, after Consideration that the Main of all modern Wit is made up of Blasphemy against, G0D, and Raillery upon Women: And can it be unreasonable to Conclude each Vice of a like Nature, when they are both found so close in Company together?</p>
<p>But, the Design of this Letter, if so Small a Trifle may pretend to any, is not to Expose such as Wilfully Misrepresent the Sex, (it would be unpardonable
Presumption to attempt any thing of that Nature, which they themselves have already perform'd with so good Success)but to Rectify the Judgment of others, who innocently enough Misunderstand it; and express a much less Dislike at the General Conduct of the Ladies, than they retain in their Minds upon that Account. This, in a great measure, is owing to an Original Mistake about the proper Duty of Woman and what her Obligations are in the common Circumstances of Human Life. For, let her ordinary Deportment never so exactly Answer her real Duty; yet, if that become Mistaken, it's plain the whole Course and Tenour of her Actions Will be Condemn'd. And, 'tis no new thing among us, first to lay down false, or uncertain Suppositions and of our own and afterwards wonder at the unaccountable Consequence.</p>
*That
<pb n="5"/>
<p>That there is a Duty incumbent on the Side of Woman, that she Naturally Owes us some sort of Assistance, or other is no more than what all Acknowledge. The Question is, in what Particulars, this Duty of hers Consists; and after what Manner, the Assistance she Owes, ought to be-made good.</p>
<p>'Tis a receiv'd Opinion, I know, that Woman is Born to Labour, and Oblig'd to, Drudgery; that she is excus'd from no Difficulties Man is obnoxious to, but
ought to share alike with him in all the burthensome Affairs of Human Life. Now, indeed, if the Duty intended, were an Obligation on her Part, to Comply with every arbitrary injunction Man might Impose or Submit to every extravagant Service he might Require, there wou'd then appear some colour of Reason for admitting this Doctrine; but certainly, the Case is otherwise, and Women can never stand in the same Relation to us, with the brutish Herd: Their Province short, is quite distinct from ours, adapted to a Distinction of Nature and Abilities and however by Compulsion or Compact, it comes to pass, that Woman frequently engages in Business, belonging peculiarly to our Sex, there are nevertheless, Visible Bounds set to her Obligations; and upon Nice Inquiry it- will appear, she is oblig'd to no Particulars lays, (at least not in the same manner) as she stands related to Man, that he is oblig'd to, in his relation to her: So that tho' some kind of Assistance be due, 'tis made Payable however, in quite another manner, than has
*been
<pb n="6"/>
been all along suppos'd, <hi rend="italic">viz. In such a manner as will prove much more easie and Natural to her self, as well as more Useful and Advantageous to us.</hi></p>
<p>Let us suppose it then, the proper Business of Woman, to Cherish us with the Charms of her Conversation, to Compose our Tempers, and Soften our Manners; to Encourage our Hopes, divert our Fears, and Inflame our Affections; to make her self, in fine, every way Amiable; omitting nothing she may safely practise for our Ease and Happiness, without Violence to her own Nature: Tho' to say the truth there is hardly need of such a Limitation; it being impossible for her, to do us any service by misemploying or abusing her Natural Powers; and she contributes not at all to our happiness, so long as she continues to *Impair her own. Hence it is, that this general View I have given of her Duty to be truly *Sensed so much as wheen it contains no Difficulty, nor any thing Disagreeable, and yet fully answers the Ends of its *Instruction. How applicable this is to the pesent Case, will appear in the Concusion of this Argument.
*What
<pb n="7"/>
<p>What the original Condition of Woman was in the State of Innocence; and the particular Circumstances of her Paradisaical Life; how large her Abilities, and of what extent her Duty, is not easily discovered; that happy Scene being of no long continuance, and but very little reveal'd relating to it. Whatever Obligations she Might lye under in such a State, certain it is, they were such as arose from the nature of her Settlement, and such as the Circumstances, she was plac'd in, requir'd: But Those have been lamentably Chang'd from what they were; her Duty therefore, consequent upon that, must necessarily change likewise: and since this great Revolution in her Affairs ensu'd upon the Fall, it will be by examining that, and a few Particulars attending it, that we must search, out her present Duty.</p>
<p>'Tis very remarkable, that the Curses of Heaven upon the Persons of fallen Man and Woman, were not denounc'd Promiscuously and alike, upon both; but Successively, and with notorious Distinction. First of all GOD address to <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi>, and assigns her the particular I punishment of her Sin; that done, He addresses likewise to Adam (exclusive of his Wife) and Curses him accordingly. Now, I for my part, am not able to conceive what Necessity there could be for so distinct an Address, unless it bore withal as distinct a Relation, nor to what purpose in the world there was a separate Cause, if they, were, to be shar'd both in common: Besides, if the Curses directed only to the person of Adam, were by any
<hi rend="italic">means</hi>
<pb n="8"/>
means applicable to <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi>, with as good reason those too directed to <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi>, must have their influence upon <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi>, in all his Male Posterity; and as soon as we Men begin to be Affected with hard Labour, and Sorrows in Child-bearing, the Ladies will in return, readily submit to all the Curses Heaven has inflicted upon us. If then, the Curses denounc'd against <hi rend="italic">Adam</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Eve</hi>, in a separate and distinct manner, concern'd that Party and that alone, to which they were each of them so distinctly Directed and it be the Duty of them both, to make Good the respective Curses, or Commands, they were respectively, concern'd in (neither of which I presume can be deny'd) it will follow then, that Man only is oblig'd by his daily Labour and Industry, to Secure a necessary Subsistance, and provide all Accomodations of Life and this, as well for the Woman; as for himself, for the Curse implying this Obligation is directed only to him; who by consequence can be the only Party concern'd in it.</p>
<p>Hereabouts I look for an Objection to this purpose, viz. That after all my Pains and Care, have at best but Struggl'd a little to determine barely, wherein the Duty of Woman, with regard to Man, does not consist; as for any thing like a Discovery, wherein it does, I have not made the least approaches towards it. I kindly undertake to excuse the Ladies (however I come by authority to do it) from the more rugged and Ungrateful concerns Life; but never think of Obliging them in the mean-
*time
<pb n="9"/>
time to more easie and acceptable duties. I take a tender Care to secure them from any Task Which might Sully the Serenity of their Mind, or break in upon the Gaiety of their Humour; but yet provide them no other Business, consistent with the preservation of these. I have advanc'd, 'tis true, a kind of Paradox of my own; but, so wild a thing it is, I have already rejected it my Self, neither recommending it from reason nor enforcing it from authority which looks at least, as if I were, not so wedded to it, but I could well enough dispence too; with the Omission of the pretended duties it contains. And at this rate, the Sex is like to prove a Very hopeful Assistance, bound to no Certain or Regular Performance, nor Determin'd by any thing but their own Humour Besides, that in the Method I have hitherto proceeded, 'Tis Impossible ever to Arrive at any conclusion in this Point; at least however to Demonstrate the duty of woman such as is pretended; for 'tis plain there is not One Syllable of what I Make her Duty to consist in contain'd any where in those Curses directed immediately to Her, out of which it was Infallibly to be Collected.</p>
<p>In order to withstand an Attack of this nature, there is no more Requir'd than to coisider.</p>* (Colon or period?)
<p>1st. Were there not the least initimation of the duty of Woman to be met with any were in Scripture; and had she no light from thence, to
*Direct
<pb n="10"/>
. Direa her in her deportment towards Man ; r& et very. likely, fhe would, in itch a cafe, have a after the fame. manner, that fhe .thanes now Oblig'd to .from Revelation : my reafon is, becaufe fhe fall's fo Naturally to the ex,a&e(} perfo17-malice of what pe eves to be herDutty ; The. Engages in
it, before the has time to make. it her.0 hotce, or even can indeed.well know. what it is. So that Pro-, Pably matters would. not ffand in fo very Deplocable a ppoflure, even tho' fhe were left altogether to her felt, both as to the manner ,and meafure of .affiflance, the, alight think good to accommodate
us with.
• 21y... It being, firft of all. taken... for gaited, that ihe, Sex owes us fome fort .of ,anitance,1v
determining once, 'Therein it does not =fifty it is
already deterain'd wherein it does,. viz. In the
l perfdtmance of ~every thing that can do. us fervice, and is not Included under fuch determination. In plain words thus ; it ' p mv'd, that 'tis no part of Woman's duty .t~ us in a Servile and Laborious way ; and it being granted at the fame time on all hands, ,that fhe .Ought to Aifi(I us ' fame way or other,. what can remain, but it muff be her Duty, to do it in fuch a way, as is agreeable toiler Inchaations, and proportion'd w her Abi-
ir	lities, viz, , So as it has been before limited ?
Now, it would be needlefs to -endeavour. a proof,
is in Duty bound to inch a_Methodof
tbat..5he r	y
Behaviours ; for it appears ;cef rily fovin.the very,
171h,A,I., j	10 .4_A\	A&tN»•.h1,Ie'	',, sPM.'	No I)	\t. 9, M':'I II' 11: I1',1, )'	.1 ,, %. ei.;`"..I,
(II
very .nature of the thing. It 'would be endlefs to defend to particulars in it, becaufe of-Their great vari cty, anfing, from fo various circumftances viz. Di-
erlty ot'Time and Place; of Perfons, and Hu1nours,. Vic. Each of which, as they differ, 'will require a quite difl'ctent management, and application.
31y. By examining the Curies denourc'd upon both Sexes; their import, and particular direction, we may gain indeed a, partial knowledge of their rcipec~ive &vies, viz. So far as they fall under . the nature Of a,Curfe. But then it were Madrid,'
by the fame means to expea any further po Itive. information. V'-pman,:we all know, was Created
for Man's Af lftance, which A ftauce therefore it became her duty to'. afloid him, not as being' a Curfe upon her (for fuch it never was) but as it was made one end abet very being. ' Now as there were more, and greater .ends propos'd herein, than the sneer fervtec of Man, fo her behaviour ought to hear an agreeable proportion to them. }lcr c'uty toMan in the mate o Innocence, coc-
:ied only of fuch actions as fuited with her own Na-Mare, at the fame time that they anfwer'd his coca ons. 1'cr it cannot without the greateI Impiety be ImIgin'd, that God would require of her either unna anal, or unneceilary Performances, that he would deign her for his own glory, and the good of flan, and yc.t*.:mai,c her rs.rcrable in her oei , and a -Burden to the ref. of the World. ' l is tree, the. Fall of Man cccafion'd an ea.:raw-dinary
D	.	change.
(i2•)
-Chang in his affairs; his former blefl'ings withdraw, and Curfes defcend, thick upon him ; yet we no where find him depriv'd ,of the. Scciety.,, and Aftiftauee of his fair Confort ; but 'when he is driven out of the blisful Gardens, the takes him by the hand, Wipes away his Tears, and qualifies the Bitternefs of fo fad -an Exile. And the fame Argument that proves her Affiftance, was tobe continudtous after the Fall, will fery to fhow it Ought to be Manag'd in the . fame Proportion as before, viz'. With a Juf} Regard to her own Nature, as well as our prefent Neceflities, Thefe are two Eileential properties of that Affiflance, we can in Reafon exile& from her and what has been Offered here to this purpofe, has the Advantage of them Both; Wherein is included nothing to the Prejudice of her Faculties or in Contradiaion to her Inclinations ; which implies all the fervice the can doe us, and what is fufficient to make
us happy. Every thing beyond it is Grievous in the Performance, and Unprofitable in the Con-. clufion. To Illuiirate this, but with one Inflance ; what would bq more unnatural than an Army of Beautiful Ladies? The foftnefs;andDelicacy of their Bodies difables them from Bearing Arms.; and the tend ernefs of their Af eEions, Indif ofes them for Blood and Ruin; their Limbs-made only for Amorous Embraces, will foon Sink under .,the rude.
Encounters of War. Their Eyes may not wound
to Death in the .'iced ; and.their. firongeft Charms
may
^+ * At. q. 1.ab c	.d. cw Y /MnVP
111 1 M y r/A. Vn yr IA'., 1i Os	0 n, ;A. 1 1, ,1	i....7.,mmenow.mumommmummmmunw.i	" ( r3)
may Fail of Captivating a Barbarous Enemy. Such conf iderations as thefe have justly Secur'd them from the. Toil and Fatigue of this Employment. And there is no Need of going Far for Argument, would that Efleaualy releafe them from every other Uncaf ie and A f fliEing work.
The natural Infuf iciency of . Woman for til e things, aireas Plainly, to what file is truly capable of. For thefe qualities, as Ufelefs, and Inf igniiicant as they appear 'to Some Purpofes ; 'Become yet Wonderfully Serviceable in a Different Rctfpe&, •; and Direaed to a Proper End. Thus what can Con-tribute more to the Improvement of Human Life, either by adding to the Pleafures of Enjoyment, or by taking off from the Burden of Evil Accidents, than a Pittiful and tender Companion ? One who Condoles our Calamities,. Rejoyces at our Welfare, and Sympathifes with every Pa[fion : One who Charms with no more than a Tranfient Glance, and Creates no lets than Tranfports in common Converfation. What then are the Etfec`s of her more familiar, and affectionate Behaviour, bf a Thou-
fand Little Endearments, Fondneffes, and Ca-	1; reffes! Thefe are:the. Labours of Woman's Life ; thefe the lnftruments of Man's Happinefs ; thus
employ'd The anfwers one end of her own Creation,	. and helps to Compleat the Dcfign of His.

W 0 M A, N
31
R i
j
.( 14-)
‘ ;41
'' W	M'
N
THE ,.
: C R W N
OF THE
o-•:,
ettatioti.	,
A	H A T has been already Confirm'd in the..
..	former part of this Letter, conerningthe
Nature and Exten of that Affi(iance de-
, I		fic,n'd us in the Creation of Woman , will be yet far-
ther Reconhinended,by confideiingliow Admirably
	well fhe Stands qualified for the Difcharge of thole	. Particular duties it Implies. This may bedone,by raping a flight Survey of her ()rigu al Endow ihments, and acquired Virtues ; which will at once Vindiite the I'erfe'dion of. the Fem,lle Mature, and . ferve like-wife to regulate out' ex c 3 ations of Advai:ta.ge :rain it.
F. T.
IIb/)
4
Ck
iffi lug 4.M',''A+,41\IV tl.: nh lu A. •M.%,'. •n1\'\'N, 4,11"ry•i1 1ir~',.,r.	>ti.A	I' ry, 11. I .,I.1 ',	I. .h.	....(15)

'§. 1.,,E DVCAT1ON.

The Main of Woman's life depends much upoa.
.. the manner of her Education : In order therefore to Declaimagainfly the former with any Colour of Reafon, or carry on the Defign with any hopes of Succefs, the latter is brf} of all to be Condemn'd.
The common method of Educating young Wo. men is frequently Impeach'd under the Specious Accusation of Vanity. And 'tis here Jut} as in other Cafes ; we foon Agree ' in the Cenforious part, to
` call fomething Vain, but. then as to the Rational, we are all Strangely Divided in our Opinions, where, in the Vanity of it does Conf it ; a good. Argument this with me, that the general Conclution is Rafh and Unreafonable. For when once an Opinion can be found°ed - upon Reafon,- it has ufually one and the fame Foundation atfiong all the feveral Abetters of it.
To' determine any anion truly ufeful; or Vain; Regard muft be, always had to its Ultimate ma., and clefign ; for without this the Inftruments of procuring the very bell of Blethngs, which one would think, are the f rthefl from vain, will never= tlrele'sbe reputed fuck And thus no kind of aftion whatever (while abflra&ed from its end )' can Pof f bly be free from Vanity : "'tis for want of this Neeeff'ary, Caution, that the Ladies are fo hardly U I'd in tlhc cal before us. Were their Education,' and
E	the•
ImiamassmimmErElgalliEligellMEMEMOMMEME
16 )
the Natural Conlequences of it but Confidered
)'		together and .with one View, it would not appear
to be Manag'd out of a Principle of vain glory, and
1;1		ollentatioa, but iudufrrioudy contriv'd for the Im-
proven nt of their Nat-are, and the retomme
uoo of their ppr	nda.
` -	'heir Leilons are law.
fOns,	..
IT- •	cent, and only ' R Lining a Litt e upon the $irn.
pl ccit~r of M Tature. , They teach how to raife	.
~	pled
1	furable Pa'lions, and Produce agreeable Ideas, to

'l	touch the Sence, and Traafportthe•''very Soul; in 14
Word, the repeated Elfa .s of their hrtl years, nee the pr a c of their duty become Habitualto them,
and t they quickly commence Artilis in the grebufinefs o!f their Lives.
s. II. CONVERSATION.
Mofi gftheCoaver, ation between man and man,
,' may be b Tided iutq In1 pia, and Contentious ; (rich as either affeas not at all, or raifes the worft- of Faf (tons- We were never deflga'd, it feats, to
' ' converfe among our felves : It is wot goad, frays the Text, rho JW¢n Amid be #l,one : but t L,adies, Beavec s be .prais'd, are Sociable, and there lies
''	grit Refuge. When we are prety.well tngp'd; with
r		iln g to one another's Dreams ;.:4r gnrag'd ,by
s utual Contradihon ; we tnay,repvr toxfiem xcfr'elhmeflt in the one cue, and in the other for
aceable Infpiraxions. Their words Ji(perfe id
nt Cares, and ,reagre the Sj ly .	; they
.	civilize
i ''' ' ( 17 )
civilize our Savage natures, and keep us from running into the Woods they Quench the unruly heats of Anger, and Kindle the Kinder Flames of Love ;they-aka in Fine the whole ConffitutiO'n, and make us eafic within our (elves; and al}~1~iCe to one another.	'
A great part of that ye ne	rtai, or fecret agree-
,	ablenefs in the Perfons of ny Women, 'tidy . : well enough accounted .for, .I believe, in their Cenverfation.. 'No Wonder we receive 'fitch Multitude of Wounds without knowing all: the'ufhiik from whence they come : The caufe is (b Ate ' 0 bvious, it (capes our nicer Confderatian. Cupid larks' under the Tongue, Wraps up:his Arrows inDelicious words, and theta alafs ! he nub need§ Kifr itl e-very Excireliion. A Woman's' Eyes indeed-c•y',fet fire to a Heart ; but when that's done it' is her Breath mutt blow it into Flame. '
'here is nothing Incredible in thefe, eff'e&s to One who is Acquainted never fo little with the natute-bf Female Converfation.' It is not Clogg'd with tbel heavy Circumftances of Bufinefs; nor made Naufeous by Pedantry, and' Affection ; it pattakes of no.-thing low, but Condefcenfion ; and All the Ninon' it admits is Love. 'Tis Infinitely Various,and Diverting in it's 1VIatter ; full of Inocence, and Inge-
,	nuity, recommended by good Language, and a grace-
ful air of Elo' ion.	'


s. III.
(i8)
t S: III. YY' I T..
The Ladies, fume of us'obferve, are not gener,aliy fo Wixty as ;Qur: felves. ; great. compliment upon them, I take it, if it were but ;loch 1n deign : : .Mop ecannot be faidin fo few wotds for their Reputation,; true Wit indeed' is, an. excellent gift, pnd
conducive ,to noble ends ; but that which ufurps to:name'of it, and.what we moll judicioufly val-
ue oury felhcs upon, is nothing but the overflow rots of a-vicious and degenerate mind ; ferviceable only to the defig , s of Malice, and` helps to bring peevtfhnefs, and the Spleen into Fashion.
_ The Ladies we fined are always pertinent in thouh „t,. as;weh-as,l1appy. in, exprefion ; and that is to be' truly witty, But, then they never recommend their parts at the, expence of their Virtue, nor. Sa-.. crihee private Conl'cience to- publick. Fame. In a a ordf.# they axe . lefs witty than men, 'tis only , Lieu* they are. better natur'd , and we have:littl~ reafce,, methinks, to boat of ours underfandings, fo long as we have great reafou to be afham'd; of our difpofitions.

I	,§ IV.V BE.A,VT T.

'Tis in vain to offer at .a general De initi)a
- of Beauty, and it can never be defcrib'd in filch a manner, as will anfwer ever' private concet .ion
of
is	-	,., 4: 1 z *u) M. i • 1	JA tx e;dt: A '•d. % 1 'AAA \'^	.	1,, q.	a	i.	.
	(19)	N. of the Thing : Unlefs it were firs polfible for Contraries to be recencil'l, or ail'' men''though t alike of the fame fubje1,
	It is without quefti4n a Peovidetnial' contrivance,	V'
	that we are all made to thinkia a; ditreretiv ttian4	av ner from one another: the. Advantage of it is rani.:
y
	ctifarly vifible in the cafe of Beauty, and our dire ent conceptions of it, .For, did every Woman, api	' peat' Egtially charmi1 iii
	' the Byes of :every 'Mad;	'
	nothing,' 'tis likely, would be afile to let bounds	, to T .n f l and Debauchery, befides I th'ot, Itnpottnce:
The Blefiing or ' handfom' Women amon& us Bears, methinks, fomme,kind of 'Refetnblance. with
r	`
	that of Manna to the Ir4eIites. For tho' 'tis true	.'v, every Particle of That, had a capacity, they fay, of Suiting with every Palate ; whereas tis not every
	Woman can make her'felf to be Admir'd of all ; and	f fo the coinparfion Fails.; there is neverthelefs an Ins
	finite varietrf of Beauties, for the like Variety of	;`. Conceptions; and the Parellel holds good in' the main, viz, that ]Here, as well as in the Wildernefs,is Meat, for every Palate ; only it may perhaps re=
	quire, becaufe it deferves indeed a little more	'	4 pains to procure it.
I take care always, for my own' part, never to decry any Woman for abfolutely Ugly ; becaufe
 • her perfon does not fall in with particular ro-,ton of what is taking, and agreeable.; for I make no doubt,bttt in.:- ail &hcafes, it E'xaalyaofwers-
	theIdea, which One, or More have Frain'd to-„them	~
felres of -a perfea Beauty.	F	§. V.
i •	c	A ..y. a..	•,i .,	y,	.~'ir a' iy,',	.r -..	i” ~.,> 'A	i. ai	C'	-i	.	r
i	.	,	iii	i	1	„	y	o i	i	i	'I	r	..)	'!/	, ~,	i ;.	1•	i.I 201,
s V. RELIGION.
The Ladies are not more unlike us in their na. tural Complexions, than in the Face of their Religion : and 'tis to be fear'd They wou'd come Off equally gainers by either Comparrfon. They teem 'to .make more of the fame Principles than. we do, and Manage them to better Advantage. They preferve the Subftance of' Religion, and let alone what ever is Snperfluous.
Female Education leads not towards any know-ledge in the Controverfial parts of Divinity and the Ladies are fo many~ftanding Arguments othe Vaaity of that fort of Study. Controyerfie, they well
". . .observe, Confounds Infieadof Confuting; and as it always fuppofes Herefy, fo 'tis gene?ally Productive of it. It is w nth good Reafon thereforethat they make no part in religiousDifputes,and thence arebetterCom-pos'd to look to their own Bufinefs, and lets fubjea to Difcra&ionamidit their Devotions : They find no occafion to judge Uncharitably of others, and there-by Secure a good 'name to themfelves.
'Tis true there are Hereticks of both Sexes, Ind.
many Women are through a Pardonable eafinefs
. of temper Seduc'd into wrong Perfwafions ; but
they rarely offer a Herefy to the World themfelves,
or 4tand in the Front of a Novel Sea. They ale
Deluded, I fay, by wicked Men ; but have no
thoughts of returning the Pious. Fraud. -To conclude,

however
1..Fu4 q 1010A ^M,.11 AA1i—nt.,1,14A,1sY.•.lV•	_.i	..
[ 21
however They may !land Difftinguif h'd among Themfelves by a difference of Faith or Profeflion ; WonderfulInnocence and Charity of their Lives will
raife them ever above the reft of the Rational World.	` I
§. VI. M,O D E S T T.	!I

Modefty is the Darling Attribute of Woman, the great Moral Diflxnaion between her felf, and Man.' This it is, that Recommends her Beauty,
and Invigorates every Charm ;. that upholds the Dignity of her Nature, and preferves the whole
Circle of her virtues Inviolable.
To talk of immodeft Women is Nonfence ; there
can be no fuck : For to loofe their Modefty, they	, muff loofe apart of their Nature; and them they are no longer Women but Monfrers : Confequentiv filch as Degenerate in this particular, bring no Scanda l upon the Sex, for they ceafe to be members of it,

§. WT. . ER_A'1NG.	I1~
We are apt to be mighty full of our felves, up-on the Score of !,earning; which, yet is the! molt Impede& of any thing about. us, and affords In-
finite matter of Hutniliation,. It confif is, for t1:c	a,: moft part,. in fenfelefs Words, and fblen-m I.~cohs in Doubts, and.Difputattons, in Pride, Prejudice ani Error.-. 'I'hefe'are the Diftinguifhing Attainments of our own Sex; and and fuch as give notable oc-
cai;cn
(22)
cafion indeed of Triumph over the other. If we pretend to any real piece of knowledge, which the Ladies are without ; we do but ditcover our Pride without having any thing to fupport it ; and become rid iculoufly Sordid. even before Pof .. fefhon. They have the fame Faculties of Soul with onr felves, and the+ fame Capacities of Underflanding; otherwife I don't apprehend how they
can be f yl'd a Thlyi eet for Us': But' 'tis their pecuiiar, Glory that they make ufe of thefe with Difcretion, and to good Effe. In aword, they have Know.-ledge fufficient to make- their Lives u f ell, and their Ends happy : and all beyond this is toilfome in thepurfuit, betides that there is no filch` thing a s pert e a A c g p n f i t on-

s. Val L0 11'E.

Love is the Foundation of Hap ' efs, and it's Eerfeaion : the Fleafures of - Earth are owing to it, and fo are the Joys of Heaven. The meat re of our Happinefs is proportioned to the Charms of our Beloved Objea ; for the more agreeable, That, the more intenfe our affeaions are, and Our felves by confequence, fo much the more happy.
All %('23")
AObjets, Conf de'; -d s Imlr,1.	-
ca~ir :",~} iciis 'we find, ju[t to the ia-nc Pied; , i1o,*
in us Equal Degrees of 1'k fare. One
Keaton of this is, becaufe they all Differ in N'a-
t -ei-an l Capacity ; and Confequently AEt not up-	it on our Minds in the fame Manner, and with E-qual advantage ; But Each according to it's proper
NNature,and Subordinate Powers. Some, for In fiance, ;	l gain -our AffeEhons purely upon the account of what they are in -themfeives; and by. the Eorce of their Intr nfrck, and inherent Ixcel encies, without any particular Endearment, or further Recommendation ; fuch are' things Inanimate, as curious Piaures, Beautiful Edifices And the like : or Even Rational Creatures them f elves , b far as they are only Propos'd
'to us with their Natural, or Neceffary Qualifications. Such ©bje&s under fo Imperfect a Notion as. thi , can at Deft but provoke a very Feeble Paflion, a Mixture rhaps of force Love, and more admiration. Other Objeas advance with yet a irong-
r C rtn, filch asin it felt is more -Powerful than all the Reif, and when in ConjunEion with them, is Irreiftable; Thefe ftrike with aDouble advantage ; The not only thine with abfolute and Intrinficic Glory They but Voluntarily. Exert It too. In fhort,
'they return ou-r. Love, and hrerigthen thatFaTion in our felves, by the Additional Powers oftheir own; and we become the very fame thing to what we Love, which' it's felf is to us.. This is the. Time,. when Mutual Defires of Union begin ,rto grow
G	Furious
	..ai
( 24 )
Furious, the Profpe& of it is Tranfporting, and the Union it felf Happinefs Unutterable,
What has been obferv'd of Love in General, will naturally introduce the following, RefleEion, Viz.
{ That .we Men are indebted to t -e Ladies, for the compleateft Happinefs our prefent .Conilitution can admit. We.- cannot but Love, as well as Ad-mire, the Virtues refding in Female Minds : And the Curious and }delicate StruEure of their, Bodies will call ever for, our Admiration. _But, then„. whep the Ladies (er l:oufly apply; all thF fe for out : Service s and' Satisfan with what Flowing joys muff' we be fill'd ! with what .. Ra tures die awa ! In a word, the, Perietion of the Periale Natwrelis, more than enough to fill our extended Capacities ; and the Pcrfa endearments of Woman-kind are able to command our utmof AffeEions, The in-fiances .of their Love are Judicious, and confequeutly Afe ,g. They are fo curiontlymanagg d and-with fo much Art, that they become no . let's
.A e
ptnl~e
in the. fmallea Trifles, than in matters of the :mat-. eft Importance. Their Love is remarkably . ' - rent from ours in two refpe&s : It is riot fo l'oon; Kind-led, nor fo quickly put Out. They cloak gratifie with their warmcfl Af dons on a fuddea: but the Recompence is, where once. they fall, they Flame,
and Burn immoveably for Ever.	.
S. IX25 )
!i IX. PRUDENCE.
Prudence is a ferious Coofideration of 'our own Conditioo,and a conQant Management of ourfelves 4. seeable to the fence we have of it. TheLacties,it m4
e confefs'd, exceed us~icr tl s rticular as- much as ip any-other. As for th o fe who.ha ,ut th 9:IA1104n upon their Minds, they may be fatisf y ed by run- . over dittina'' the feveral Circumstances, Rclati , and Capaciti s, of al, of ;any individual of the *Ix, and obt~erving her proper Cr re, aad P udenti~al Co - du& thereupon: }I r ?eve}lion to }leaven, arid: C rity to, Man-i:u?cl; Her flay to Parents; and t fr -to Children, Her Love to her Husband, Her Clem} .cy to Servants, &c. And Afterwards by. look ing,,back -upon therrownB viQurin,fp neofthefatpe,or ,pare ellel cafes; and obfervingthe many,Abfurdrrues come mitred in each of them.
DIVERSie .+
'Tis a common Complaint among the Enemies of the Fair Sex That too much of their Time is '	fpent
S'
f pent in Eafe and Pleafure, and confequently too little of it Referv'd for BuIinefs, and the necefl'ary charge of theft Duty. I o v this O aje in Will appear Frivolous, and of no Force, if we do butconfdcr it's, fir{ } , Rife It ,proceeds from a miftaken
Duty • 'G iierrai	Thefe Men look
upbir 1.,abo~,tr ttn , fi	t ,ns ' ~ ,ci tial to
o
the "ctfoth nce of Meyer is -Cortimanded by Au.
tI tity ; the it	4W rl'hi±! is then daBolt,
„, .mac	4>	fi Vin ibn and Paiu . ,Thus
Perlonll
khe~i~	tnd to a more
{	than ordinat'y share f Tteligi i, oiil becaufe t4ey
f	'1b11Pe i t itmfc~-esf'hanO	didiabout
-it ; 'afrd were Aeaddy'toCondein alfuch. ass ferv'c
-bklt rft#Ay	~k a mortRational Freedom
.i	Innocent T ro -ret#tent Of Life. .And” thus 1
liperfvra ed it is 'with t'he,Men I am now .~r
• ng 'et They	dt lGw the Ladies to be ,'ing
t elirl Dtity,fe-letig they it thesnifetues to o vifi-
'hle '~ ~ltr ~t -1t	d o it y when at the rattle
time the only way for them to do it •. El&ually isw
do it Delightfully, and after their own Humour. They are naturally Difpos'd to accomplif h thofe Ends
for which they were defign'd ; and they then take the readiaW- *ay tro Attain =ems .w .they purfue them in a Manner moll Eafie and Pleafant to therm.
{elves.	(27)
to kinder Influence upon tile, Mind- of Man bah Wom nSiaging ? What will fowler Raife his Drooping Spirits, or Slacken his ftormy R.elblution ? What can we defire more than to hear the Voice of a.Syren,and never feel her Violence ? What joys like thofe of being Ravi. fh'd with theMufiick,withoutbeing Ruin'd by the Monf cri.? The Ladies are all Sincere.; their Songs full of Harmoiiy and Love. And IbalI we be Offended at our own Happi-
	nefs, becaufe the Authors of it are Partakers with its, and	. repeat with Mature what we hear with Tranfport ? Shall we deny the Sw.eetnefs of the Charm, or not admit it, to our Ears ? 0 fenfelefs Obftinacy ! 6 barbarous Stupidi-:ty
Again, Nothing adds a:diviner Grace to the Pcrffn of a Woman, than a proper Mo,;ion, a becoming Mien.
ve , was, no longer Ignorant of the Qoddefs his Mother, than till the Mov'd : He knew; her. by her heavenly Gate.
There is n4any thing mare Affe ilg,, among all; the silent Endearments of the sex. CAp;dlil eo.Yces-at a Duncitig ,Match, and Triumphs at _a.Bafl ; acid, flaI we Cosadamnthe Ladies for ufing fuch an ~ ierci fe ?, ! For t, y part, I fee no place for Cenfure : Thofe Who do, I remit to the former part of this Letter-, where they will find, That the Life of Woman ought to be Eafie, as well as llfefpl ; and the may very reafonably confute her own Happillefs, eV en there; where the is principally promotirg Ours.

Thus, ,/i,fad rt,- have I attempted, your Commands, c. c; cording to that Brevity, and Method, You were pleas'd t ) Recommend, I haue given you my Thoughts, wherein tl,e . proper Bufiriefs of your Sex, fo far as it relates to our o wn, does confift; and confider'd Briefly, how well you are difpos'dhy Nature and Inclination for it.
H	The
(T2J')
The CCrrclnfiQn of all is, That you Ladies :vt e c ;o be Hippy yourfelves, and to make vs fo , a A at
'if
your
own Happiads-is .the Era. End of our ownEeing, fo'tis the f rff Step too-to-the" Happrnefs of ours.
This Argument might, I csnfefs, be much improv'd by making ufe of different Coofderations, and enlarging farther upon each : But you guefs'd aright of my-Incapacity, and ,accozdingly confin'd my Pcn. Nor have 1 cauft to Complain of the Rei aint ; fo 1 have lb fhamefuly manag'd the Bet ufe in this little Compafs, that a ggreater Liberty could have only turn'd to my greater Confnfion :-
„ -B hall this Acknowledgment of mine, is downright Tranf greff*ng the Charaaer_ of my. own Sex. 'Tis much more Natural for us to be Conceited withourown Performances, to magnify a little Merit in our own Eyes, and. then.dai nn a Reward .as Vaft as our partial Imaguaatlon. ,You mud needs be Senfible, Madam, of this common Infirmity among us ; and I befeech you,. Confider it : For there,s nothigng elfe I know of can excu fe me, if in conf deration of this lm-
1	pew} Trifle, I refum to do my fell lb much I3ouour, as to:Snbfcribe my Pelf,
Madam, with all ,3Kmility, year mo, , f asthfi !` Servant,
Philogynes :
ems, ,,
r'	430
ilir' f
