THE SPIRIT OF THE CONFEDERACY

“Unveils a Picture Of Morn and Night,
Yet sweeps the lingering mists away!”

By Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers
Poet Laureate Of United Daughters Of The Confederacy
Georgia Division.

“Tis Morn in the Southland.  Upon each hill,
There gleams a tint of gold, and in the vale afar
Resounds the merry call of one who keeps
The wandering lamb from straying o’er snowy field
To vie with each whose store shall weigh the most,
Or who at eve shall bring the finest yield?

Peace, Holy Peace rests o the Plantation Home,
From teeming Orchard to the Garden Gate,
The sun-lit heights fo “Georgia’s Old Red Hills”
Bespeak the calm that rests upon each State.
King Cotton proudly smiles upon his royal seat,
While Autum fruits their countless joys displayed,
And golden grain breathes life and health complete
For Heaven’s touch on every spot is laid!

The Light of Holy Writ beams on the sacred hearth,
No prowling Bandit there!  No evil soul to roam,
The Master Mistress, Child and good old Mammy knelt,
To thank the Lord for peace in a Christian Home.
Out own dear land!  Our hallowed Southland Home!
Was there ever another spot like thee?
Where dependant friends (not slaves) who with life’s last breath,
Despite the War, could true and faithful be?

And was there ever a Christmas Time so glad?
With Banjo, Violin, Song and Dance that filled 
The heart with joy over-flowing and merriment unrestrained 
In honor of the family whose wealth they helped to build?
But list to that destructive March o’er Georgia’s peaceful soil
Tramping over human hears they hasten to the grave.

‘Tis Night!  Darksome Night!  No star illume the way.
Then Statesmen soon on terms of Peace, three different times were sent
But not received!  For other views prevailed
Against all sovereign rights of State Coercion as intent.
Then, the Spirit of 76 illumined all the South,
And steel met steel alike with American zeal anew,
Till “The Stars and Bars” at Manassas brought forth a ray of light,
And proved to all the spirit which King’s Mountain found so true!

All Battles were unwelcome – but homes in ashes laid
Brought forth in words immortal emblazed upon the air
An urge unto the spirit, in light that cannot fade,
This slogan of the Daughters – “Live, Love, Think, Pray, Dare!”
Then the Holy Spirit guided – and compensation came
When Davis, Lee, and Stonewall add Righteousness to Fame,
And ‘neath Heaven’s Light inspired still forward moved the Gray
E’en though their number lessened mid storm –clouds all the way.

So ‘twas the faith of our Fathers that gave courage to the true,
And it led by God’s own Spirit all our Southern Soldiers through
Not a soldier of the Southland under General Lee’s command
Would rob one of his property, or flash the fire brand.
All Honor to their Memory!  All Hail their names tonight!
And to all who served their Country in Justice and in Right
May Daughters of the Confederacy the Gates of Love unbar
And lead the Blue and Gray as friends to Heaven’s Crowning Star!
