ADVICE To the WOMEN and MAIDENS OF LONDON.

<p>Shewing, that instead of their usual Pastime; and education in Needle-work, Lace, and Point-making, it were far more Necessary and Profitable to apply themselves to the right Understanding and Practice of the method of keeping books of account: whereby, either single, or married, they may, know their Estates, carry on their Trades, and avoid the Danger of a helpless and forlorn Condition, incident to Widows.</p>

<p>With some Essays, or rudiments for young beginners; in twelve Articles.</p>,

*By one of that sex.
LONDON,
Printed for <hi rend="italic">Benjamin Billingsley</hi> at ,the Printing pres in *<hi rend="italic">Cornhill</hi>, 1678.
<pb n="1"/>
*ADVICE 
To the WOMEN and MAIDENS
of
LONDON.
*Ladies and Gentlewomen,
<p>Permit one of your sex to give you, as far as <hi rend="italic">her</hi> small knowledge will reach some hints to the right understanding of Accounts: an Art so useful for all sorts, sexes and degrees of persons, especially for such as ever think to have to do in the world in any sort of Trade or Commerce, that next to a stock of Mony, Wares and Credit, this is the most necessary thing.</p>
<p>Nor let us be discouraged, or put by the inspection thereof by being bid meddle with our distaff, for I have heard it affirmed by those who have lived in *forriaign parts, that Merchants and other trades men have no other Book-keepers then their Wives: who by this means (the Husband dying) are well acquainted with the nature and manner of the trade, and are so certain how, and where their stock is; that they need not be beholden to servants or friends for guidance.</p>
<p>And for telling us that the government of the House
*apper-
<pb n="2"/>
appertains to us, and the trades to our Fathers or Husbands; (under favour) the one is to be minded, and the other not neglected, for there is not that danger of a families overthrow by the *sause wanting *it's right relish, or the Table or Stools misplac't, as by a widows ignorance of her concern as to her estate, and I hope husbands will not oppose this when help and care is intended to them whil'st living; and safety to their name and posterity after death: except they have private trades (too much in mode) whereof they would have their wives wholly ignorant. In such a case indeed, one that knows not that one and two make three suits best. And let us not fear we shall want time and opportunity to *mannage the decencies of our house; for what is an hour in a day, or half a day in a week, to make inspection into that, that is to keep me and mine from ruine and poverty.</p>
<p>Methinks now the objection may be that this art is too high and mysterious for the weaker <hi rend="italic">sex</hi> it will make them proud: *Women had better keep to their Needle-work, point laces, &amp;c. and if they come to poverty, those small Crafts may give them some mean *releif.</p>
<p>To which I answer, That having in some measure practised both Needle-work and Accounts I can averr, that I never found this Masculine Art harder or more difficult then the effeminate achievements of Lace-makeing, gum-work or the like, the attainment whereof need not make us proud: And God forbid that the praise of an useful Virtue should prompt us to a contrary Vice.</p>
<p>Therefore if I might advise you, you should let the poor serve you with these mean things, whilst by gaining or saving an estate you shall never be out of capacity to store your selves more abundantly with those trifles, then your own. industry in such matters could have ever blest ye*
*And
<pb n="3"/>
<p>And now Gentlewomen I give you those rudiments of Accounts, which are the subject of this little pamphlet and transmit this learning to you the best I can, in the self same manner as it came to me.</p>
<p>Know then that my Parents were very careful to cause me to learn writing and <hi rend="italic">Arithmetick</hi>, and in that I proceeded as far as Reduction, the Rule of Three and Practice, with other Rules, for without the knowledge of these I was told I should not be capable of Trade and Book-keeping and in these I found no discouragement for though <hi rend="italic">Arithmetick</hi> set my brains at work, Yet there was much delight in seeing the end, and how each question produced a fair answer and informed me of things I knew not.</p>
<p>Afterwards I was put to keep an exact account of the expence of <hi rend="italic">House-keeping, and other petty charges, my. Father made it my office to call all perfons to an account every night what they had laid out, and to reimburfe it them, and let all down in a book, and this is the way to make one a Cafhicr as they are termed, and one that. can keep a fair account of receipts and payments of Money or Cafh-book, is in a good way towards the underftanding of Book-keeping shee that is fo well verfed in this as to keep the accounts of her Cafh right and dayly mitred in a book fair without. blotting,- will loon befit for greater undertakings.
Now in regard that other !earnings do depend upon this petty 'Caffi account ; I find it therefore convenient toa give you an example of a moneths ex pence, and you. will thereby fee what further ufe may be made of it afterwards.
Therefore to begin, my Father gives me at fcveral times in the moneth of yanuary, the lulu of 21 1. 17 I. z rid, the account attic expences whereof is as followcth.	Exe
(15)
I have not further to fay, concern-
ing this Account of Houfe-Expences, but, (that at the Years end, when the
Account is pail and approved) there'
fhauld be a Scheme thereof drawn out of the Paid Account, in manner follow-
ing, vt ..
The
(14)
I know not any thing that wants Explanation in thefe two feveral Accounts, except the Reason of the Figures preceding each Summe of Money : The life there-of is this. In the firft Account , pag. 4. The tint Artide is 4d. paid for a Book ; and the note of Reference thereto is 12.. To thew that you have that Sum, and that parcel pail to Account in page t 2. And in page 12, under the Title of Books and Schooling, I find the numberof Reference to be 4, (hewing that the Paid Entry of 4d. for a Book, was there Originally Entred, viz. in..
pag• 4.
Now, why all this, you'l fay a
I Anfwer, were there no other reafoa than that , I might (from the fecond Account, wherein I do only fet the Sum, and not recite for what) turn the readilicr to the firft Account, and fee what it is for; this would recompence the trouble : But there is a further and great ufe thereof to be made its the keeping an Account of Trade, as (hall be (hewn in due place.
And I do not doubt, but, that if Paremsand Superiours imploy their Children or Servants (one at a time, That is, one in one Year, and another in another) in this or the like way of keeping the Accounts of Houfe Expences, or other petty Charges (beIides ;he fatisfaUion they will have to fie how, and which way their Money goes.) They will alto train up their Children to be regular and handy in Accounts of greater Mo• merit,
