<pb n="[iii]"/>
*PREFACE
<p>AS the following collection of receipts cannot fail of being useful, both to families and private persons, I can only assure the reader that they are the result of long experience, every one of them having been many times tried, and none of them ever proved ineffectual.</p>
<p>It is well known, that the woman who is ignorant of cookery is neither qualified to be a mistress or a servant; for the dressing of victuals, either in a plain or a more polite manner it so essential a part of female education, that those who neglect to acquire some knowledge of it, labour under many difficulties in their advanced years, and many have lost very *valuables places for the want of such necessary qualifications. But as it too often happens that women neglect to learn those accomplishments in their younger years, and as the memory is not able to retain every thing, I have undertaken this work for the use of my Countrywomen, and
*am
<pb n="iv PREFACE"/>
am well convinced that it will answer the most valuable purposes, let their situation in life be either high or low.</p>
<p>With respect to cookery, every thing has been inserted according to the practice of the present age, and nothing left out that could be useful, so that either the mistress, housekeeper, cook, or servant may at all times find directions for the dressing of victuals in any manner whatever.</p>
<p>By this assistance, the mistress of a family will be enabled to give proper directions for preparing every necessary entertainment and those under them will be directed how to act in a proper manner, by only turning to the receipt in the book, where they will find the quantities of the ingredients properly arranged, so that no mistake can happen, unless they *wilfully neglect to abide by the instructions.</p>
<p>But besides cookery, which is, absolutely necessary, less or more in every family, there are proper directions given for all sorts of confectionary; the best methods for preparing made wines, and the most approved rules for pickling. The brewing of such malt liquors as are used in families, is pointed out in the clearest manner,
*so
<pb n="PREFACE v"/>
so that the person who attends to the different directions will be enabled to discharge all sorts of domestick duties.</p>
<p>The rules laid down for the preservation of beauty are, not only simple, but all of them have been tried, and may be used at any time without the least danger, they having never been known to fail of success,*</p>
<p>As many families are situated at a distance from gentlemen of the physical profession, and as some disorders may be cured in an easy manner, I have here inserted receipts for such diseases and complaints, as are common in general, both in children, and those of more advanced years; to all which I have added proper instructions, to servants in cleaning furniture, washing, smoothing, and many other articles, absolutely necessary to be known by those who would acquire the character either of industrious house-wives, or good servants.</p>
<p>Upon the whole, nothing has been wanting to make this the most complete *book of the kind ever yet offered to the public, and the author doubts not of meeting with the approbation of those who peruse it.</p>
*THE
<pb n="[153]"/>
*THE LADIES COMPANION FOR THE DRESSING ROOM.
*CHAP XVIII.
*<hi rend="italic">To make Pomatum for beautifying the Face.</hi>
<p>TAKE a handful of oats, and stick them in the fat of a bacon hog, newly killed, without any salt; let it melt before a slow fire, and when it is quite dissolved, put to the dripping a spoonful of the oil of cinnamon, with the same quantity of the oil of sweet almonds; when you have mixed all these together, let it be laid up, and it will make a most excellent pomatum.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To make Water for beautifying the Face.</hi>
<p>Take a quart of white wine, and the same quantity of goat's milk, mix them together, and grate over them a penny loaf, and a pound of double refined loaf sugar; squeeze into it the juice of four lemons, and add to the whole a great house-leek, three ounces of roach allum, a few-water lillies; a handful of white poppy seeds, as many bean blossoms, and a few violets; when all the materials are bruised in the liquid, let them be put into a glass alembic and distilled. It is not only useful in beautifying the face, but will also give a fine colour to
*the,
<pb n="154 THE LADIES COMPANION"/>
the hands and neck, making them, appear white and transparent.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To preserve the Complexion, and restore such as are decayed.</hi>
<p>Take two scruples of saffron the same quantity of camphire, two drams of dried quinces, as much water lillies, blew violets, vine leaves, mint, tendrels, red roses, and myrtle berries. Mix all these together, then make them up in little balls, let them dry a day in the sun, then beat them together as small as possible, in strong vinegar that has been boiled; squeeze the materials out of the vinegar, and make it up in little balls of the size of a hazle nut, which when dry you must dissolve in a gill of Benjamin water, and it will either preserve or restore the complexion.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">TO take off red Spots from the Face.</hi>
Take a lemon, and lay it before a slow fire, in a flat earthen plate, to receive the liquor that sweats out of it; when all the juice is out, pour it into a glass to * and rub the face with a few drops of it, which will *move all sorts of red spots.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To soften the Lips.</hi>
<p>Take an equal quantity of fresh butter and fine virgin wax, put them in as much rose-water as will cover them; put them in an earthen dish over a slow fire, and when they are melted thoroughly, let them be put into an earthen pot to cool; a small bit of it rubbed over chapped lips, will soften them and make them quite easy and agreeable.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To remove Pimples from the Face.</hi>
<p>Take an ounce of burnt copperas, the same quantity. of starch, and as much brimstone; beat all these together, then dissolve them in rose-water, put them up in a chrystal bottle, let them stand a week, and when you want to use them shake the bottle, and rub your face with a little of it, laid upon a soft linen cloth.</p>
*To
<pb n="For the DRESSING ROOM 155"/>
*<hi rend="italic">To make fine wash Balls.</hi>
<p>Mix two ounces of cloves with the same quantity of sanders, and four pounds of the best white soap cut into small pieces; put to it twenty grains of musk, dissolve the whole in rose-water, then make it up in balls for use.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To take away Wrinkles.</hi>
Take two ounces of the powder of myrrh, lay it in a small fire shovel till it be red hot, then take a mouthful of white wine and let it fall gently upon the myrrh, which will smoke up, when you must hold your face over it, so as to receive as much of the smoke ,as possible. "If you hold your face over it till the whole is wasted, it will have a wonderful effect; but if that is too painful, you may cover your face with a cloth.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To make fine Imperial Water.</hi>
<p>Take an ounce of gum arabic, the same quantity. of frankincense, mastick, and benjamin, which you must dissolve in five pints of French brandy; put to it four grains of musk, two ounces of the kernels of pine apples, the same quantity of sweet almonds, half an ounce of cloves, and as much nutmeg grated small; when all these are beaten and mixed together, let them be distilled in the brandy over a slow fire, and bottled up for use.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To make a Water for giving the Countenance a most beau-blooming Colour.</hi>
<p>Distil four ounces of honey, in five pints of vinegar; while it is over the fire, put to it an ounce of red sanders, then let it be set to cool and bottled up. Let the face be washed clean before you use it, then take a little in a cup, and when you have dipped a fine linen cloth in it, rub your face gently, and it will have a beautiful blooming colour.</p>
*To
<pb n="THE LADIES COMPANION. 156"/>
*<hi rend="italic">To make the Face, when over red, appear fair and transparent.</hi>
Mix two drams of camphire, with two ounces of borax and one ounce of roach allom; add to them a pound of allom that has been burnt, put all these in water, after you have beaten them together, mix with it the white of two eggs, and when the whole has boiled an hour, pour into the vessel a pint of vinegar, then let it be taken off and let to cool; after it has stood about three weeks it will be fit for use in the following Manner. Wash your face with fine white soap, and when you have dried it, dip a linen cloth in a cup full of the liquor; rub it all over your face with your eyes shut, but do not wash it with water any more that day.</p>

*<hi rend="italic">To remove slight marks made by the Small-pox.</hi>
<p>Take half an ounce of Venice turpentine, the fame quantity of sperma ceti, and one ounce of olive oil; melt all these together over a slow fire, until it is beginning to boil, then take it off and let it stand a few days to settle. When you use it, rub it over your face gently and the marks of the small-post will disappear.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To hide deep marks made with the Small-pox.</hi>
<p>Boil an ounce of sperna ceti in a pint of malmsey, until it is quite dissolved, then put to it the juice of a house-leek and that of plantane leaves, mix with them half an ounce of peach-kernels, and when they are all properly mixed, let them be let to cool, strain off the liquor through a fine cloth, and when you rub the face with it, let it be warmed gently in a cup.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make an Ointment for a Ring-Worm.</hi>
<p>Mix a spoonful of in mustard with two ounces of Honey, half an ounce of popillion, with as much ceruse; mix the whole together, and when you use it, rub the face over three times.</p>
*A fine


<pb n="For the DRESSING ROOM 157"/>
<hi rend="italic">A fine Ointment to make the Hair grow.</hi>
<p>Take a pint of sweet-oil, and mix with it a handful of fern-roots burnt to ashes, put to it for ounces of linseed-oil, an ounce of bruised almonds, with as Much mastick and fine honey, put the whole into an earthen. dish; let it stand over a slow still fire till it is so hot that all the ingredients are properly mixed, then let it be let to cool; when it grows stiff, dip it in clean spring water, and make it into a roll for use. When you use it, take a piece of thin leather, and lay it at night to the place where the hair has fallen off, in the morning when you take it off, wash the place, then comb out the hair gently, and after you have repeated it three or four times it will begin to grow.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make the Hair grow thick.</hi>
<p>Take of southernwood, hazel, bark, rosemary, myrtle berries, and maiden hair, each two ounces, lay them on a red hearth, or in an oven till they are reduced to ashes; put the ashes into a quart of white wine, so as to work it into a strong lye; then let it to cool, and rub the hair with it as hard as you can.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make a fine wash for the Teeth.</hi>
<p>Mix an ounce of bole-armenic in a gill of hungary-water; put these into a quart of claret, with two ounces of honey, an ounce of myrrh, a dram of allom, and ten grains of salt of vitriol; let them stand in an earthen vessel, or in the jar three days, then set it up to settle. When you use it, put a spoonful into a cup of water, and wash your teeth with it every morning; it will keep them white and preserve them clean.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To fasten such Teeth as are loosened.</hi>
<p>Take a handful of the leaves of a damson tree, and boil them in white wine, then strain off the liquor and let it to cool; bottle it up, and wash your mouth with it twice every day until the teeth are fastened.</p>
*To
<pb n="THE LADIES COMPANION. 158"/>
<hi rend="italic">To take away Freckles from the Face.</hi>
<p>Take four spoonsful of bean-flower water, and the same quantity of elder-flower water; mix with them one spoonful of oil of tartar, when they have stood two or three days, and are properly fettled, rub a little over your face and let it dry upon it.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make Sweet Bags to put among Linen.</hi>
<p>Take a clean bag, put into it four ounces of roses in powder, two ounces and half of labdanum, four ounces of marjoram and orrice; calamus aromat, benjamin, cypress, *suffis, white saunders and sprignal, each two ounces, civet and musk each one dram, lay the bag among the linen and it will smell sweet.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make a Powder of the same Nature.</hi>
<p>Take an equal quantity of the following articles, so as the whole does not exceed a pound, viz. Lavender, white sanders, basil, marjoram, cypress, calamus, calaminat, benjamin, orrice storax and cloves; mingle with them a handful of dried leaves of roses, put them in a bag and let them lay among the linen.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To restore the Face from Sun burning.</hi>
<p>Take half a pound of tartar, and beat it up with the same quantity of salt-petre, lay it upon a polished marble stone, and set fire to it with a hot iron, take up what remains after it has burnt two minutes, and put it in a bag which must be hung up in a cellar, with a vessel under it, for it will dissolve into a fine oil; put to it four ounces of vinegar, with half a pint of clear spring water, four ounces of lithrage of gold, mix all these together; when they have stood a day, they will be fit for use, and look as clear as rock water. Rub your face with it when you go to bed, let it dry in, and when you get up in the morning, take a piece of scarlet cloth, rub your face with it, and the whole will come off; then wash it with fresh barley water that has been boiled
*with

<pb n="For the DRESSING ROOM 159"/>
with plantain leaves. Repeat it every night during one week, and the face will regain its former colour.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make an oil for the Face.</hi>
<p>Mix the flowers of beans, water lillies and roses, in a pint and a half of new cream. Put them in an earthen pot, over a slow fire, and let it boil about ten minutes, take off the finest of the oil that rises up, set it to cool in the air and then bottle it up for use. It is an excellent composition for cleansing the face at any time.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make a fine Pomatum for the Skin.</hi>
<p>Cut two pounds of hogs lard into thin slices, wash it clean, and let it soak ten days in water, only remember that the water must be as cold as possible; and changed once every day; then melt it over a slow fire, skim off any impurity that rises to the top, when melted pour it into cold water; wash it clean with rose-water, and rub your skin a little with it.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make the Eyebrows appear Beautiful.</hi>
<p>Mix with the blood of a young cock, half an ounce of emmets eggs, the same quantity of gum of ivy, colsphonia and burnt leaches when they are all dissolved and mingled, put them up close in a wide mouthed glass, then take a pencil, dip it in, and touch with it those parts of, the eyebrows where you want the hair to come off.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make the Hair of the Eyebrows grow regular.</hi>
<p>Take two ounces of linseed-oil, half an ounce of lead filed as small as you can, with a dram of maiden-hair; mix with them, two drams of henbane-seed; beat them up together in a marble morter, then put it up in a vessel and use it in the following manner. Take a small piece of black silk, dip it in the ointment, lay it upon the eyebrows when you, go to bed, and when you take it off in the morning, take some white wine, wherein myrtle-berries have been soaked and wash them.</p>.
*To
<pb n="THE LADIES COMPANION. 160"/>
<hi rend="italic">To change the Colour of red Eyebrows, to a fine black.</hi>
<p>Burn a handful of cherry Bones, and the same quantity of ivory saw-dust, when they are almost thoroughly burnt, grind them as small as flour, mix with this powder as much oil of amber as will make them a thick liquid, was the eyebrows with water in which black cherries have been boiled, let it dry in, then take a pencil, dip it in the composition, and rub over the eye-brows three different times, letting it dry between each, when it will appear as black as jet.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make the Forehead appear extremely Beautiful, and enaging.</hi>
<p>Take an ounce of mastick, and dissolve it to a jelly in half a pint of piony-water, take it out, and spread a piece of it on leather, lay it on the forehead, with a ribbon tied to it to keep it tight; this must be done when you go to bed, let it be pulled off in the morning as quick as possible, and the scattered hairs will come, up by the roots, so that in a few days the forehead will appear very comely.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To prevent the Hair from growing on the Forehead.</hi>
<p>Take a colewort leaf, and put in it two ounces and a half of henbane-seed, then put it into a piece of brown paper that has been dipped in water, put it into embers that are not so hot as to scorch it, let it lie till it burns soft, then take it out and beat the seed together in a morter, mix with it a little oil of walnuts so as to moisten it, strain the whole through a fine linen cloth, put to it two grains of orpiment beaten to powder; lay it on a linen cloth, and tic a fillet round the head to keep it on during the night. In the morning when you take it off, rub the forehead over with pomatum, and wash it with bean-flower water.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make the Nose appear Beautiful.</hi>
<p>Take one grain of musk, a scruple of spikenard, dried roses, and cloves, of each two drams, beat them together, with a little white sugar, and mix the whole with
*a glass

<pb n="For the DRESSING ROOM 161"/>
a glass of white wine, then make up small boluses, and when you have occasion to use it take one, which you must dissolve in rose-water, hold a little to your nose, and wash it with the rose-water. It will remove all disagreeable impurities in the nose, and make the breath smell sweet.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To take Worme. from the Nose.</hi>
<p>Take one dram of the powder of sulphur, two drams of unslack'd lime, and infuse both into a gill of lemon juice; put them in an earthen vessel over a slow fire, until they are dissolved and properly mixed. When you use it, dip a feather into it and rub it all over the nose, when the worms will die and fall off, but as they will leave pores in the skin, rub your nose with oil of almonds which you must wash off with juice of lemons, and you will not be troubled with them again.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make fee red Pomatum for the Lips.</hi>
<p>Take an ounce of bullock's marrow, the same quantity of fine white wax, and melt both together with three ounces of pomatum, put to it a dram of alkanet, and let it stand in an earthen vessel over the fire till it has acquired a fine *redish colour, take it off to cool, rub the lips with it, and they will appear of a fine blooming colour.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make a fine Water for the Gums.</hi>
<p>Take six ounces of spirits of wine, half a pint of water, four ounces of scurvy-grass, one ounce of cinnamon, two drams of cloves, of red roses and lemon, peel, each half an ounce, mix the whole together, then beat them in a morter, where they must stand a day; then let them be distilled in a glass over a slow fire. When it has been set to cool, let it stand some days, then take a linen cloth, which you must dip in it and rub the gums.</p>
*To
<pb n="THE LADIES COMPANION. 162"/>
<hi rend="italic">To strengthen the Gums.</hi>
<p>Mix a dram of allom burnt, with two drams of the peel of Seville oranges, an ounce of cloves, half an ounce of cinnamon, a pint of Malaga wine, and the same quantity of water distilled from briar leaves; put them into a glass bottle, and mix with them two ounces of virgin honey; set the bottle over a slow fire, or rather on embers, where it must remain five days, then let the liquor be poured out, into an earthen dish, through a thick linen cloth, and bottled close up. When it has stood a week, wash the gums with a little of it, and they will regain their former strength.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make the Breath smell Sweet.</hi>
<p>Mix half an ounce of sanders, with cloves, nutmeg, and cinamon, of each an ounce, put to them half a dram of musk, and the same quantity of aloes, dry them before a slow fire, then beat them to a small powder, which must be fitted through a very fine sieve made of lawn; then put to it tome rose-water, double refined sugar, and gum-fragrant; make the whole composition into small pills,and hold one of them in your mouth at least an hour every morning, or during the time you are dressing, which will make your breath sweet all the day.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make an Ointment to beautify the Neck.</hi>
<p>Take two ounces of the marrow of calves feet, one dram of camphire, half an ounce of the oil of myrrh, and the same quantity of the oil of spikenard, put to them two ounces of the oil of sweet almonds, and one ounce of the water of tartar; when the whole is properly mixed let it be put into a canvas bag, through, which you must strain it, and when it has stood a few days to thicken, let it be put into boxes for use. Rub a little of it over the neck, and it will give it a fine colour, of a mixture of red and white.</p>
*To
<pb n="For the DRESSING ROOM 163"/>
<hi rend="italic">To make the Shoulders and Breast appear white.</hi>
<p>Take a quart of dew gathered in May, with half a pint of sumitory-water; put to them two ounces of lavender-water then let all the ingredients be properly mixed, and put up in a vessel to settle. Wash your neck, breast and shoulders, first in water that *camomile flowers has been boiled in, mixed with white wine, let it dry in, and then rub this liquid upon it, and the skin will appear quite transparent.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To beautify the Face after the Person has been afflicted with the Scurvy.</hi>
<p>Take of rose-mary flowers, camphire, and frankincense, each a dram, infuse them into an ounce of fumitory-water, mixed with half a pint of, white wine. When they have stood a night and a day, let them simmer in an earthen vessel half an hour over a slow fire, then pour off the liquid, and when it is cool, rub the face with it.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To prevent the returns of Eruptions by the Scurvy.</hi>
<p>Take half an ounce of the roots of jelly-flowers, one ounce of the juice of lemons, a dram of aloes, and two ounces of *pellitory-water; when they are all properly mixed, put to them two drams of oil of myrrh; let the whole *soke together twenty-four hours, then strain, the liquor through a cloth, set it to cool, and rub the parts offended with it.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To make the Hands Soft and White.</hi>
<p>Beat in a morter two ounces of blanched almonds, with four ounces of the flowers of beans; put to them four ounces of Castile soap, with a pint of rose-water; then let them be all beat up together, and when you use them for your hands, moisten them with.. warm milk.</p>

<hi rend="italic">To prevent the Skin from peeling off the Hands.</hi>
<p>Take four drams of pomatum, half an ounce of fine red wax, two drams of oil of roses, two drams of borax,
*with
115.lr Txa LA•DFES.00NINA NION.
with four ounces of venifon fewet; hold them over a,: gentle fire till they begin to melt, then make them, up into an ointeaent, which. you mull lay upon the hands when you go to bed, and in. the morning let it be wafhed off with warm milk. Continue to do fo three nights fuccefiively,., and then the hand will appear white and beautiful.


To fecrrre Nails that are likely to fall of.
Take a gill of white wine, two drams of powder of.. acrimony, and- the white of an egg, , beat them all up together in a morter, then flrain the liquid into a wide mouthed bottle where it mull iland to fettle, ,then take a linen cloth dipped in this and rub the nails, with that .. part of the finger above, them, and the mails willxemain firm.

To prevent the. Skin from growing, over the Nails.
Take a fcruple of falt-petre, two drams of barley meal, adram of'fugar-candy, and halfa dram of powder. of callus; put to them as much honey as will make a thick liquid for a plaifter, put it upon a piece of leather, and clap it upon that part of the finger where the &in is like to grow over the nail. It has been often used with great fuccefs, and feldom ever failed, nor is it attended with any danger to the perfon who tries
–
T'o take Spots out of the Nails.
Take tsuo drams of. Venice turpentine with one dram.. of myrrh, mix them together over a flow fire in,an earthen vefiel ; then fet it to cool, when you mull fpread a small piece upon leather, and keep it all night ration your nails. Do it three nights fucceflively, and the (pits will difappear..

rho re over the Colour of Nails, that have become black by haling.
Mix two scruples of flour of fulphur, with two drams
of capons gtcafe, ..and the fame quantity of oil of camo-
mile;
aFor the DR E,S5t`fYCryKOOM.	r65
mile ; put to it a dram of the. oil of roles, and *a few grains of cummin-feed ; mix the whole together,. and lay a (mall bit. on leather,. which. malt be pit to then.ails when you go to bed.

T'o make a fine Water for *whitening the Skin.
Grate the' crumb, of a penny roll into a pint of new sulk warm from the cow, put to it one ounce of the roots of daffodil,, and two ounces of the roots offnakeweed, let them,. diftil in a glafs over a. flow fire two hours ; then put to the ingredients,. one pint of, hun-,gary-water ; when you have ftrained out the liquid, fete it to cool,. , and mix with it a few grains of mufk, with a half a-pint of fennel-water, then. rub the fkin, all over, and it will appear tranfparent.

2a make fine balfamic Water
Take four ounces of borax, a dram of mufk,, a. fcruple of ambergreafe, three ounces of white dittany, with an ounce of each of the following articles, viz.. aloes, aloes wood,.ginger,, cloves,, myrrh, frankincenfe,., gum- arabic,,gum-ivy,.oil of bays, and apound of Venice turpentine ; infufe the whole into four quarts of brand* dy, and beat them together. in a morter, then fqueeze - the liquor out, and put it up in, bottles for, ufe.. When rubbed on. the akin it makes it .look foft and. agreeable..

Io, mak, fine Water to fof en the Skis.
Mix. together. the flowers of lavender and fumitory each two ounces, one ounce of frankincenfe,, and a quarter of an ounce .of camphire ; put to, them two, ounces of orange flowers, three ounces of, rofemary, and one ounce and a half of the flowers of balm
pour upon them half a pint of the fpirits of wine,. and fix pints of white wine, let the whole fteep together. twenty-four hours, then take it and rub the fhoulders,. breafls, and neck ;:, it will make. the skin feet as fmooth, a,' fattin.
;		16011111111
Tthet	1 H E, L Alike 15	k.	wi r. et i-i F lI l `1
To make a fwarrhy Complexion appear agreeable..
Sift the flour out of half a peck of wheat bran, then, put to the bran eight new. laid eggs,.. and fix pints of white wine vinegar ; let the eggs be beaten as fmall as . pofliible, and when the whole is properly mixed, let its diftil over a flow fire ; when it. has flood a. day to fettle, take a little of-it.and rub yovr face every day for a fostnight, and it, will look extremely fair.

¶I,'o make fine waif; Balls to bgea stafy the Hand, and Face.
Mix together a dram of nutmeg grated fmall, four, ounces of benjamin, one of orrice,. three of ftorax, one of dried peel.ofcitron, half an ounce of cinnamon, .and
,
the fame quantity of cloves, put to theca one ounce of. pomander, and half an ounce of yellow fanders•;, beat; all up with four ounces of Cathie foap, to which mutt be added as much rofe-water as will make the whole in
to a fine pane ;, then make it up into little balls ;which to preferve the (cent mull be rolled in almond powder,. then let them be tied up in fine writing paper, and put in boxes till you ufe them.

To make a Perfume for taking aevay,all.Sorts of dcfa -reeable
Smells.
Take an,ounce of the oil of turpentine, half an ounce: ofkwood of faflafras,. one dram of fulphur, and an ounce of frankincenfe, with the fame quantity of cedar wood;, when you have rallied the wood finall, let the whole be mixed up properly into balls, and when you finell any thing difagreeable in your chamber, burn one of them, and. that will remove it.,

To make fine fleeted Selig:
Take a morter, hold it over the fire till it is warm,... put in it a pound of fnafr that has been mixed with. herbs, when you have melted upon it a.few grains of ambergreafe, beat the whole. together till it is properly, mixed, then rub fuck as flicks together with your hands till it is loft, fill it up in tin boxes, already prepared. for the purpofe, and keep it for ale.
.
`ro.I;Fen the 'DRESSING-ROOM.
TO make fine liquid Snuff for the Brain. Take eight drops of oil of lavender, and the fame quan-
', tity of mace, fix drops of marjoram, two pounds of rofe• -mary flowers, and let the whole be fteeped three days in a pint of benjamin water ; .keep it doled up, and when you are feized with a weaknefs in the brain, or land the approach of dizzinefs or other fits, hold your •nofe to the vefl'el, and .you will, in lefs than a .minute, find yourfelf perfealy well.

To make a fine .waling Powder.
Take four ounces of the flour of French barley, two ounces of 'the ail of fweet almonds, fix drams of benjamin, and a handful of the leaves ,of white roles, half . an ounce of fperma-ceti, one ounce of white chalk beaten to a powder, and a quarter of an ounce of white tartar-, one fcruple of the oil of cloves and lavender ; mix all thefe together, then beat them to powder in a morter, and keep it in a box to be ready when you wash your hands.

TO make perfumed Palle for Bracelets.
Take half an ounce of turpentine, four grains of ambergreafe, and the fame quantity of muck, put to them a dram and a half of calamita, two drams of benjamin., and of the following articles half a fcruple each, viz. flowers of lavender, cloves, mace, and wood of aloes; let the whole be difl'olved in as much rofe-water as will turn them to -a -pafte, then let them be beaten.together in a snorter, and put up in paper for ufe.

To make a Perfume to carry in a Box in your Pocket.
Take two fcruples of the flowers of benjamin, half a 'fcruple of the flowers of roles, one fcruple of orange peel, a little nutmeg grated fmall, efTence of cinnamon and orange, each a fcruple ; mix with thefe half an ounce of jeltamine butter, a few grains of mufk and amber ; beat them all together till they are properly mixed in a morter, then put the powder in a box.

4n
eke
	Imo
ifs Tut LAD11;t,CO P'ANION
• 4n • excellent Perfume to be ofd when you die afraid
noxious Air.
To ode dr a of me& of Alexandria, 'dd an equal
luantity of_ amber reafer two i ruples of the oil of rhodium, and as much balfam of Peru.; one dram of yellow fandees, half a dram of calannita, cinnamon, cloves --and mace ; when you have beaten them all together, put to them t'o drams of civet, then let the whole be ;put into a box and kept in your pocket. .

iiir excellent Remedy for Freckles in the Face, that feldom fails of Succefi.
Mix an ounce of lemon-juice with two ounces of Venice foap, add: to it half an ounce of oil of almonds, and the fame quantity of oil of to Jtar; fit it•in the fun, and keep furring it every daytill itaecofnes• -aid, then fofteu it with oil of rhodium, and keep it for 'ufe.

Another Remedy for Freckles, of a tom finple ,Ngkrs, 'which may be ufed.when the Complaint is not fo inveterate.
Mix with oil of rhodium, half an ounce of oil of tartar, and an ounce of oil of fweet almonds. Let them (land together in a veflel three days, then rub the face over with it, and it will regain its primitive colour; only take notice, that altho' it makes your akin fmart, yet it will not do it any hurt, for that fn+arting is a lure fign that it has operated.

`-'a remove from the face, Spots of- a long Standing.
Difi'olve in a quart of barley-water, two ounces of benjamin, and the fame quantity of ftorax; put to it a pint of brandy, which will give it a fine redifll co-lour. When you ufe it take a baton filled= with clear fpring water, and pour a few drops into it, which you malt mix with the water, and then rub it on your face.
EVERY
A	1
E V E R Y • ' lie A `• I) Y ' '
HER OWN
PH 'SICIAN.
C	...A P.	XVIII.


re prevent a Confumptiox, whore you have Realm is fear
its .Approach.

TAKE two eggs new laid, and let them hand is
,j the embers, until they are quite hot, but not hard, then take them outs and when you have made a hole in ou end.poury out the whites; put.into the e.!pty part'o the eggs & r anion, f'ugar and'rofe water, then fiat them again in the embers, and when they are et}otigh'take them up and eat them.
TO prevent ldwx_yi of Spirits.
Mix a gill of Pack with an ounce of fyrup of cloves, a'$i,nt of mint water, and a pennyworth of faffron, put then all together into a bottle, and let them nand about a week, when you may drink a glafs of the Iigti'br as'octen as you' find a return of the complaint.

Sr'o prevent faintiieg Fits..
Take of oral*' a flowers, and damage rites each a drain,' compound pinny-waters, and strong cinnamon, tviodrgmi'CaCh ; anu with them a fcruple of Gafcoign's
Q	powder,
powder, three drams of fyrup of gilly flowers, and a drop of oil of cloves, put the whole ingredients into a bottle *ith ttwp oultces ttf :watt w en .tilat cherfriet have been Reaped, and let it land a few days, then it will be ready for ufe, and a glafs mutt be taken when you dread the return of the fit.

rl'o create an ,Appetite, and present the avant of Refl.
Put an ounce of bark to a quart of the infufon of bit-ter fimple, and mix therewith two ounces of 4y ticum helvetic, let it ftand doled up in a,bettl> a week; anyl take four fpoonsful of it about, two, hours laefore dinner,
.W
repeating the fame practice ten days, and you will have a good appetite for dinner.


.c?fne Powder to ftrengthen the Brain, aid prevent HyfterlcFts.	As
Take two drams of white pony root, one dram of white briony, two fcruples of fait of amber, the fame quantity of caftor, and four drops of ,oil` of'.amber,; beat them all into a powder, and keep it to take in the nofe like fnuff.

2'o make a fine Cordial to prevent the Palpitation of the Heart.
Take eighteen grains of faffron, clipped final], two fcruples of cochineal, four ounces of black cherry wa. ter ; digeft the whole together for an hour over a flow fire, in an earthen veffel, then pour upon it a gill of good canary ; when you have fqucezed the liquor thro' a clean linen cloth, add to it cloves, nutmeg, and oil of cinnamon, each two drops, one yolk of an egg, a dram of the fpirit of lavender, half an ounce of the fpirit of rafberries, and one ounce of gilly-flowers, mix the whole up together in a glafs morter, and it will be ready for ufe.

For .Aguifh Complaints in general.
Mix ten grains of powder of crabs claws with fifteen

grains of fait of wormwood, when you have beaten
them
EIE	S,I IAN. i,t

them tc-getlaeryelydtrs sport tlrtni {ome e+i dt l Water and teiteialfe,At dtta -s a$ar titney. wlrerr yon lopeft,the Man
,for . at I'&rt idn- Agee; or that Slott ' L b return- -once ire

: thew When the third fit is over, and-you begin to expef} a- return, infufe two temples of jefuits bark into a glafs of wine, .and ink it up; continue to do fo after the Is io oises~, and, when, you have taken: it about fifteen timesi pima ivrth filet the ; ague beginning at) 'leave you. sAs Tome perfoxaimayoaot like the bark upon, aecount of its sitoirne1s rtalrt;yrnay put: to at- as'm ch (gar as will fweeten it to your talk.
Weauaryyfer• inttxariting Feelers.
' Mitt one,buiiccof flake mot with a pound of jefuit's llmi6; both beaten into a•pewder,••atr infifed into as
vstis up of cloves -ae a illaiake eleQuary. Between the fits take about the bignefs of a chef-nut, andwhen you have repeated that about three or four days, you will fin,ill tis giowing utter, and wiiffo,n alto-be well.
i) ;!	r	. r a	.
) - Qo f eogtbtnthe Stomach. .
' . Take 'of Spatial:angelica root one dram, the fare qquuaixrtity of calarnus arornatirusy two drams of gentian &ott,i'roman''wormwood; in (Li tope ofceamany, each a Flasrrter:of a, hBtldful; -put to them 'half a•drain of cori.  laielet,ifeed,, nd,dst twlaoteifkittner inJaa earthen.veffel over a ,flow hare, with a Fiat of clear ,piing water ; then let the liquor be firmed off, and put. to it four ounces of gentian water, pet it to cool in a bottle, and drink two fpoonsful of it in the day, one when you get - up; in ; the morning, and the other about five in the afternoon )but you mull. not. eat any thing till an hour
afcerwartla.
vai
.e	;:d vfofiil Receipt t o;iborerryent an 1f hint,
Take half a pound of elecampane, roots of fennel awdxpariley each two ounces, white horehound, maiden-
hair,
II
172	E	R	D
hair, hyfop and fcabious, each an • prince, nettle and, crefs -feeds with orrice each half ,aa, au s'~e, four wawa• of bay berries, half an ounce of cummin-feeds +,arid two. drams of fpikenard ; fteep the whole in-a gallon of white wine, then; pour off the liquor and cil.tt ;: drink one gill every morning when you• get up,. and you will fin!
. great benefifrom it.

do Ele7uary for a violent 4Qbma..
Take half an ounce of liquorice:powder, ,four ounces. of purified honey, flower .of fulphur>.annifeiel; and elecampane, each three drams ; mix all thefe•together, and take about the quantity of a nutmeg three-Dr four times, a day.	=,z

F o r a v i o l e n t C o + w g & e r r i n g ,
Infufe three drams of garlack, ,and half en- ounce of muflard feed into a, quart of. white&wine °ltt.it ik.04 a week doled up, and drink at glafs of, it; as,.; oftz 1& y u
pleafe.	g . t . ,
In excell: tElixir1 or pbs Chie,tough i*	ldrtest..
Take of liquorice root and honey, each four ounces, flowers ofbenj,amin one dram, half adram of annifeed, two fcrupks of camphire, and an ounce of (alt of tartar; infufe the whole into ,a quart of reitified fpirits of wine ;. let it digefi in the liquor about four weeks, only that you muff take care to flake it once every; day ;:them let it be (trained off and.bottled up_for. vie. G,ive,tho-child from five to twenty drops,. according to its age and ftrength.

?'o make peElo, al Pills for an 11•/Ihma..
Mix of orrice, liquorice, and powder of elecampane, each one fcruple ; two fcruples of fugar candy, and half a fcruple of flower of benjamin ; pux to..thcfe. s much balfam of fulphur as will make it into pills ; then take three in the morning and the farm number when you go to bed.	,
A RkmtdyI ER. 0VlfN WWYST'C1AN. zj
d Rcmed*Ar efr . Brun.
n Mix a large hattdh'wi`of,parIle 'with half a pound of fresh butter ; chap -the,whoie together, and let it be ap-.aplied warm tm the wound.
9' cure inward Bruifes.
Take two drams of white fugar candy, one dram of fperma•ceti, when you have grinded them together, take as much balfam of fyrup, as is neceilary to make itinto'pills, then beat the whole in a morter with a warm peftle, and, take,four of the pills at different times of the day.
For flopping the Blood of a Wound.
Take two drams of the c€kothar of vitriol, wafh it clean, from the faits, and apply into the cut nor-wound ; it •feblom fails of fuccefs ; but where that cannot be had, take a cobweb with a little chalk, and put to the cut, tie it clofe up in a linen rag.
T'o cure a Burn. '
Beat two drams of fait with two raw onions, in •a morter, and when they are properly mixed, apply foine of,it. to the part affe&ed.
An Ointment for Chilblains, Lies, Whitlows, fee. in Children.
Take fix-drams of 'wheat flour, ten drams of 'honey, (even ounces of g6tid'fiWli 'batter, rain and wax each four ounces ; when all three, are properly mixed, fpread tome of it upon a piece of leather, and apply it to the part affefted, taking care to change it as often as it grows- hard.
Another approved Remedy for Cbilbaixr, Fie.
Pare off the outfides of half a dozen of turnips frelh palled and lay them on a plate before the fire till they, grow foft, then 'let them, be tied on the , lie as . hot as the patient can bear them. It is ufed in many places pfthe country with very great fuccefs,
Q-3
q~it
Y .E.'R Y L A I	,. i i
cure Claps.
Mix three ounces of beef feet with one ,e unee of bee's; wax, half an ,ounce of Strafburgh turpentine, arid as. much oil of bitter almonds, as,,will make. it „adto.an, ointment ; when the whole is.melted, anoint the chaps. with it as hot as the patient can bear,. and the parts wall. .be whole in few days.

.B ufeful Poulticefor Wbitlo vs..
Take eight drops of balfam of Peru, two drains of common rofin in fine powder, mix with them the yolk of a new laid egg : let the whole be beaten together, and made into a poultice to lay to the fore.

A Poultice for kibed Hide.
Rcaft two turnips, an4 two onions, then put to them an ounce of turpentine, make the whole into a-poultice, and lay it on the fore.

For Gripes and Worms in Children.
Take two drams of rhubarb, annifeeds and liquorice each two fcruples, two ounces of (toned raifins,. and put the whole into a bottle with a quart of mild ale ; when, it has flood a week, let it be firained into another bottle, and give the child a fpoonful in the morning..

An excellent Remedy for the Cholic.
' Take of orange-peel what quantity you pleafe, and when it has dried as much as poflible, let it be beaten fmall to a powder ; when the fit comes on, take front half a dram to two fcruples.

TO make `I'inRure of Rhubarb for the Cholic.
Lnfufe into a quart of brandy two ounces of rhubarb, cut into thin flices, and let it fiend a week : when the fit comes on, take three ounces of it for a dofe; but if the patient has an averfion to brandy, then take the fame quantity of cinnamon water.

'or
tee.
II > 'RIF. 43=w N.: P''fit WS feel A- N., ~"or Beth Cbolicr psi are: act rded via,
Yorniting,.
-'Take of compound ,wormwood and black cherry wan.-'I er, . each. two ounces ;, an.. ounce and a ball' of lemon
- juice,. one dram of falt of. wormwood, one ounce of: fyrup of poppies, . one dram. of fpirit:of.mint, and the fame,,,gpantityof.compound lavender..;- m;ix.all .thefe to- - gether, and take three fpoonsful when the vomiting ceafes,., ,and in . mofi cafes it will prevent the. return of the fit..
.F Medicine for, the We of theft Ladies who are aflic`ted
with a confumptivt Cough. by taking too: much Phyfic.
Take a dozen of fine raifins of the fun, flit them open and take out the kernels, then. fill them up with
fmall tender leaves oft rue,... and let the -perfon aflii led	{ take them as foon as fhe awakes .in the morning and net eat anything till two hours after, or if the can fait till noon it will be the better.

fl nouriAing Medicine for confumpti'ue Ladies.
Take a dozen of cray fifh.of the fmalleft fort, gut, them clean, and,let them be boiled in barley water,, until they t become of a redifh colour, . then take them . out, , and,beat them with the fhells,in a morter.till they. are as foft as mafh; let the juice be poured out, and given to the patient in an equal quantity of chicken, broth, or any other broth that is not too'ftrong.

2'o make. artificial Afjesl6filk., , .
Take two ounces of, farfaparilla, fix drams of thin thavings of ivory; two drams of fafl'afras cut thin, an ounce ,of antimony beaten to a powder, and tied up in athin linen• rag ;, put the whole into two quarts offpring water., which mutt be boiled till it is- reduced one half; then itrain off the liquor, and put to it two drams of. bruifed liquorice ; take a gill of it three times a day mixed with a fpoonful of warm milk.
lr
milt*	0
*II"	E. V-	LAn
Aeoriial Roller to be tiler in Few'.
T ke half,a fcruple-of	' (os efanr'ih 'tamp'
tity, of crabs ; claws, five grains' di ~peiwlerol ' ;. F .6 mix the whole` together and make	tips its `a3 'l F
patient.

eWafers to be taken in Fivers.
Take one ounce of tamarinds; the fame quantity
the juice of Spaniftelrquorice, math the'whole togetl1er -
in a molter with two drams of gum' 'tra inth;{ thtn-
lay the compofitron on trotdtes~ arid' 1'etlt~ei&be fit 'to
dry, in a flow oven. They are to be -grin one' at vtltote
to the patient,, to beheld in the mouth,, as they contri-
bute to alevia-te-dtoagfiit, . by" lee O iii lltd'mouth moiit.-
t	7) i )'Iw s' `o tot.
N': B . The above medicines are'	Ta iti =f'eversdn
general, And' are'all lefts or Mori 'iif 1; liat'thEre'lifdeig

• fo many different forts of .fever's, mid' attended :ii th (Itch a variety of •fytrtptoms; blia~t fhe puff g7ho i~idlfld prefcribe for particular ones,pught: to be well acquaint-
ed with the cotilli'tntlOit of tb •p	nt, gthertwife he
3nay do tore harm'thatii glaid:' Infd eit'	f refore,
it is the duty of die- perfr{tf^ a	t , Or ii el 'Nfrie	ko
fend' for-A'phyfician, who updn'exami'rting' into t'hi itit-
• ture of the diforder, and the patients eonftitutiotI fio I1 know what to-apply, .	'

Remedy for the yellow :71undice.
Mix two ounces of fumitory, ,with herfaitte quantity of the fyrap of borage,' and : a handful of-round headed meadow fennel, let therh be boiled up -together, and the liquor given to the patient to drink:

An' excellent Receipt for the Rbeurnatifm.
Take purflaim, water fillies, and `water of lettuce, each - four: ounces; ' fyrup of violets *arid fyrup at lemon one ounce each ; let the whale be Mixed togethe and given-to the. patient tie drink.
4'tiot btr--,.rH E°R CYW 14_ Ft14''Q' SI L .
aiiw'ther Pimellyi,the dawfAih std o? 4t:	t
.rTakeagt	s <ofi	i	r
each half ardrime,Atom 4fiMakes r~
oiitlae
, the whole up into bolufes, of which one muff be taken i when you go to bed; and when, y begin to fweat, ketp drinking' liege poffet, taking great-care too-avind .catching cold.;.
:4not ten .,Remedy,`- cheap, and r f ful in pear ::Ranrilies,
rMart.pills of-Selo turpentine that has been wafhed clpassy; *8ti.tutlxed.with powdered liquorice;i take tvrta or three firft in the morning and fait at-night.:

1l Remedy for 'tbe Scurvy in Winter.
.Takexfour,harndfuls of pine or fir tops, :and let them b citIl'i#tell, half an ()dunce of winters, hark, pnt one' quart of water to every twenty ouncesi and, whew atw boils, pour into it four ounces of juice of dandelion; when it has boiled half an hour legit be taken off and fee,to cool, then put to it half an ounce of fpitit df fcurvy-grafs, horfe-raddifh-water, and fyrup of elder berries, of each four ounces, let it Rand a day to diffolve, then let the liquor be ftrained off, and a quarter of a pint taken twice in the day.

To f rengtken the Stomach by an external Application. Take mint, wormwood, and mugwort, an ounce
	each, beat them tggether in a .glafs or ffone, morter,	jthen take a ...little of the mixture ,and lay it upon the
flomach when you go to bed.

./t Medicine for the Gravel.
Take two fpoonsful of the juice of onions, and mix it with half a pint of white wine when it has {toed a, few hours, let the patient drink of it, and it will give him immediate relief.
Another Medicine for the fame.
Take a glafs of water, and put in it a fpoonful of
oatmeal, when it has Rood an hour ftrain the liquor,
and
Y s r	.' .Y Ei R. 1- i 1. Ad Der	s	t.

and pat to t'ad onful„of clatified, honey ;:'take four Omar r timesi t1tie,m oruing WRing, nu ,td W a little water, : and it will give immediate ea(e.

For a fort Mouth.
_Take half a pint of clear water, and boil in it a leaf of fage; *hen it has boiled ten minutes, fet it to cool, then put to it four ounces of white wine vinegar, two ounces of honey, and'fix drams of roeh-allom 'e; it on the fire to boil again, taking care to* fcum it half an hour, then fet it to cool, and walk tfiaanuuth' with it in the morning.

Another for she /amt.
Mix with one pint of red wine, two drams of powdered myrrh, and drink a little of it in the morning when you get up.

For a Whit/or.
Beat a dozen of fnails in a Hone morter, then lay them on a piece of leather and apply them to the parts affe&ed, keeping the plainer to it about twenty hours, when you take it off %ou may put another ;o it of the fame, unlefs the pain be removed.

4 Remedy for Worms in Children.
Take two ounces of diddled water of goats rue, and put in one dram of clean quick-filver ; let it fland all night, then drain it through a fine linen cloth, to prevent any dregs getting • into it, and give it at one doze to the child.

A Worm Pc'wder for Children.
Take mineral of ethieps, and powder of coralline, each fifteen grains, two grains of fafiron, and mix the whole into a powder to be taken at one doze.

Foe Worms in grown Ferfons.
Take two ounce of alexiterial milk-water, twenty drops, of elixir proprietatis, made with felt of . tartar,' epide
HER OWN' 'P1d Slse RYA If. .
etiOemic-water, Alt pi	wood, each one
drub, let them be	WA1s irie &i iiatt alien
when you waken.' ii tbtmc	e

Far an tx uai Ceagb ';ar a iil Tee.
Take three fpoonsful of hyfop-water, as 4 oise ounce of fine fuggar candy beaten to a powder, keep it on the fire 'till `the t is di'ffel*d,, but it mutt not boil, wh& ~ it 'kastfleed to -cool put to it an ounce of the' oil of ftveet almonds, when the whole has Rood about two buttes (hake them together, and give the child two or three fpoonsful every day according to the feverity cif the cough.

An internal Remedy fr. the- Rides in Children.
~~`: T>olte o charts-tongue-water four fpoonsful, of 'the fyrup of cloves, clove gillyflower, and hyfop-water, each two fpoonsful, twenty drops of oil of fulphur, and it child's.fpoonful of alkernies ; mix the whole together in a bottle, and give three fpoonsful to the child every morning till it be all ufed, and if it has not fucceeded, you may repeat it again.

A external Cure for the Rickets.
Take one pint of the oil of neats tea, a handful of dwarf elder, and as much cammomile flowers, beat the herbs in a morter, with the oil, then let it be fet over a flow fire; whgrt it has boiled half an hour let it be. taken off, and the oil Brained through a cloth ; when you ufe it, anoint the child all over before the fire, except the head, ,and give to drink hyfop boiled in fpring water.

For heittjhefs in Children
Take of crab verjuice ,half a, pint, two fpoonsful of the juice of rage) put to them half a pound of loaf fugar grated down, when your3save mixed them together, let them boil till they cott>ie' o fyrup, give the child a little before it-fucks; and if it is troubled with a phlegm give it fotne morning and evening,
R	'xf.
	EVE RN .LA,b'Y	-
For a	amt in the Ear.
Take half a pint	-wit t+viiuice:`"`-
gary.water, an ounce and a half of honey of roles ;
them together, and when, you have fyringed a little int. the ear, dip a piece of cotton in the oil of almonds,, .and flop it up fo*a.day.

For a Noye or -Ringing in the Ears .
Drop, oil of bitter.almonds, mixed with oil of cloves on a little,cotton, fqueeze it into the ear, and lie tome time on the contrary fide; do this when you •go to bed, and.drink wine mixed with.rofemary to make youfweat, keep yourfelf warm, and the ear clofed up.

TO take,ap, Niel out of	Zar.
Take oil of bitter almonds, and tinture of myrrh.-each two drams, oil of favine, ,and wormwood, each ten drops, when you havemixed all ,thefe together, pour a few drops in the car, and it will either draw out the infect or kill it.
THE
,`4+44 +44
THE
FAMILY INSTRUCTOR.,,
CT:A•1Nt,N,G


A. great variety of she moll approved R E c a Z po;. neceffary to be known bye" L A D Y, H o v a z-
Lt*P fit, shd SBitv*N-T. CHAP. XIX..


7o deflrey hulk?.
A K half *00 of the bell reAified. f hits of
Twine, loch as is ufed in lamps ; put to it half a pint of new oil of turpentine, when you have mixed them together, put in the liquid a kw bits of cam-.
rei srsd at - let them be *$Taken two o 'tl rey times,. then dip. in-it a fpunge or linen rag, end wlh the furniture with, it. where the vermin are lodged, it will kill them as loon as they are. touched with it, and the quantity mentioned in this receipt will ferve for any bed whatever, fo that you will know how ouch is wanted for the wlyole houfe.

.mother Metheil-roving Buggs.
Tpke as much oil of la's a stae, and foap lees-as your furniture requires,, rub the. icd1teads,; &c. over with it, and fmoak the room .with brimlone.
Ra
otiY
I
'f 3f4,THE FAMILY INSTRUCTOR.
9"o de~ro, R4# , ea s .	2i4cc i OKs ,
Mix crude mercury with arfenick, and rub the cempofition over pieces of fat bacon or cheefe* fpread the pieces in different parts of the rooms or out.-houfess where they ark: moft numerous, and all fuch as tafte of it will die. Be careful to give notice of it to every per-ion in the family, becaufe many fatal accidents have happened where that was neglected.

To prevent Weafler from fucking Eggs.
'tit a handful of rue in'each of the hens, ducks or geele aeils, and the wcafles will not come near the eggs.

defray fleas.
Boil wormwood and wild cueu bers, *lade the room with the water, and lay between the mat and the bed, herbs called hounds tongue, and arfomart, which grows wild in the ditches.

2'o dg(i ro Lice.
Make an ointment of hog's lard, the juice of rage, and a few grains of quick-filver, rub it on the iktn, and in the hair, and the finell will kill the'' ter= min.

T'a kill Flies.
Take two or three handfuls of helebore, bruife it fmall, fteep it in new milk mixed with orpiment, (prin. kle the room with it, and fuch as do not die, will removq from the place.

T'o deftrey Moths in Hangings.
Take fulphur and ftorax, and burn them together in the room, taking care that the doors and windows are all fafely flint. The fmoak will kill them, and you will not be troubled with them again for fix months, when you may repeat the fame experiment.
ThE.F'AM I-L,YNT-RUCTQR 1St
To dejlroy Mots axlft Cloatbs.-
Take fiowers of`.'lavrndtr, fitsWas wood, with leaves of rue dryed; mix them together, and fprinkle them upon your cloaths both linen and woolen, when, you put 'them up in drawers or trunks.

Tode roy Worms in Brdfleads and other-wooden Furniture.
Take, a fufficient.quantity of vinegar, and put to it brimftone and ftorax, then wafh the furniture with it, and it willdeftroy the vermin. This is commonly ufed in librq.ries, to prevent the worms from eating the books, the method is to take out the books, and when -the (helves are fweepedclean, .wafh them with this mixture..

o males Candlefticki and other Brafs Furniture, of a fine Gold Colour.
'Put an ounce of burnt roch allom, into a pint of ft ap lee, .boil them together,.and rub the brafl'es with it, let, them Rand to dry, and then rub them over with trip i, and it will not. only. remove all Plains or fpots, but a o give the brafs a moft beautiful colour..

vi'-,give	fine lrif .e to Silver and Plate.
Pirit let it boil in'lye, and when you have taken it out, . rub, it over with whining and Pet it to dry, then rub off the whiting with a woolen cloth, and rub on the plate burnt .,am ; ` it will give it a bright luftre.-

4'o give faded Paintings' anew G?of
Boil an ounce of glass-wort, and the fame quantity of.tattar,. in a pint of,watar. till it be reduced on: half, then let it be ftratned off, cleanfe the (tuft fro.aa. the paintings, rub the Iiquid over the paintings, and they will look as bright as at 'fir*,

To Rive a fi w JJufFre to: faded hangings.
foal : fullers earth, and;* cake foap in water, than $taut. it of into. another veflel, fcvwcr the hang_ia, s
R. ;	eta
I
.186 Tits FkiMiLY 1NSTRU'CT-OR,
in the (trained ..;water; then, rime them . in fpring water, wherein. fomeallom •hash been dif olved when they are dry rub them over with the juice of lemons and quinces.

2'o peke Linen cloth extremely white.
When it has been well wafhed, let it be laid on. the grafs in a hot fummer day, and when it begins to of y, wet it five or fix days with water in which allom and chalk hath been difiblved ; waft it, and. when dry it will have a fair white colour.

I'o take Greafy Spots out of Saltine and Sills.
Take the bones ofihee s trotters, and when you have burned them, let them be beaten to powder, lay the powder on a piece of white paper on each fide of the place where the (pot is, take a lighted coal, and when you have put it in 'a fpoon, fet it upon the upper fide of the cloth where the fpot is,, and the heat well make the afhes fuck out the greafe ; then, take a piece of fine wheat bread, and rub on it,. until you fee nothing of the Rain left.

T's take out Spots of Pitch, far,. It offn, or Bet's Wax.
Dip a feather in oil of turpentine, and rub, it over the fpot as often as it dries, and when you have done fa five or fix times, the stain will be removed.

TO take out Stains made by Ink or Fruit.
Mix the juice of lemon with that of onion, and rub. it over the main, and let it dry, then wafh the ltain. with foap diflolved in vinegar; keep the linen in chamber-lye, and wash it out in a ftrong lather, made of cake foap.

To take iron Mauldr'outof. Linen.
Let the linen be ftrft well wafted in boiling water,. anoint the place where the mould is with juice of _ fennel, when it is dry, let it be wafhed out in fine Caftile foap, and the Rain will be quite removed.
Tx' . p''A Irt11 Y IN 'R >l e A ' R. 'tar--
I e take Speer made 1 rJail er	rwhite,er1rtd Saki.
Witeneymi hit* wee thotliliunsritlu f', is =®rf: wine,..
:rub shover with nit 'wh rof- an;eggs ltet€ t' Airy in the fun, then wafh out, and let it bewell.prelkd

To- take Spotr ortt of Crivxfon.Yehvet.
Rub the fpots over with force ftrong aqua'v'itte„ then, rub, on, the fpots whites of new laid eggs,. let it dry ia.: the fun,, then bruin it. off, andwrthc colour, will be as frefh as ever..

2'0 take Spots out of Scarlet..
Take the juice of lanerice, and when you have laid' it on the`fpot, let it remain an it threehtwlrs, then wafh it in warm water; if it does not,:da at the 'firft, add to the juice :a little foap, and it wi31 take take it oust effect.. tuallye
?a:	=Spots- oatr e Chet in {issiun,
Take of white leap, roach allom; and tartar-of tonnes,.. ..three minces' each,. and, make them into a fine powder, 'put the whole into an. eartloeu.pot,, over a flow fire, where it mutt remain till.it begins_ to hanmery then puts to it an ox's gall;~ with Rime allots water, let them be .bailed ttogf'thett.•'and wail the fpots with'it while it h. het .' vepeat +Thee times,. after which let==it';be washed in firing water, and the fpots will` be enitirely, eradicated.,	.

2`o take Spots one of all Sorts of Linen.
Take juice of foreel, heat it well over the fire, then tub it rrpod''tl fpote,- and. if it» in l'u naer, let it be hung; up i>tr the Arlo dry., and the fpots will difap. pear.-

,ro take Solt or Stains from- t3sl~fii?rxdr.
M,ik'a linall' tt ey f1* fait with juice af-lemo>tr wraii ~tlque:parts than-am 'ftawt4d', -and'let'them city -grad-natty, when-yon ttt tom: fG-'$ r o or four times, the fpots will be gone..
2's
i
	Vii
r0t3. Tn+e F M-IL Y N'S T l U C'O R.
To clean Chairs..,
Drop fame linfeed upon a woolen rag,- rub the-chairs with it, . and. then rub them hard with a dry cloth until they appear-bright, take a, hard brufh, rndarub upon it fome yellow bee-wax, brulh them all over, then rub them a with rough woolen cloth, and they will lcold as when new. ,

re clean `fables. -
Firff rub them hard with a cloth, then miz:linfeed " oil with brick-duff, and rub them over till they are: quite clean, take a hard brufh, -and when you have. rubbed uponit Tome yellow bees-wax, brufh -them` till; they are fo clear that that you, map fee your face in therm
take a flannel cloth and tub them clean, and :they, will, have. a :fine appearance..'

&e bell Way ra eltan a Rbem.-
Let the mop and the brufh be rubbed with they grain; . that is with the length-of the board, and not acrofs the breadth, neither let: the -boards , be wet too much, for that (oaks in and hurts them •; take fome fine-dry fonds and take care you. do not wet too much of, the room at once, but as f<)on as it is dry rub the, fan& upon it, - and then fweep itoff as clean as poble ; rub the fkirting boards with a piece of flannel, .and they, will look as if newly painted, but take care that the. oil .do not tquch the floor, for that will ffainit.

re clean Stairs. .
The• method - is 'mach the fame as that. of cleaning - room, only take care. to have your, face always to tht afcent, which-will enable you to give them i fine co-lour ; let the hair-cloth be fwept once every day, . aria once a week taken. up: and. doffed, • then fcour them, and when. dry lay ,on the cloth. lithe ffairs are of f}one; let them be fcoured with land aid water, but not with fire fl<ones,, s that is ap,t to make an imprefl'ion on the Repo, aid fpoil theirbrauty,
eft'Trts If AihfPLY INS`'P&QCTQ Pt.,
iV
o keej ;Stair:, ra4jv f r	4	" a !r 'r'
tj mfgur +Zt~t	itl	i	l
Take a few haudfi is of mint, lan ey, n halal, Frew them	the,1oor14 ;0*. ,at,tf'r:. p 1eev.	4 them,
clean,, t	take a lgag hardabru ,~ h, eg ns
upon the boards till they appear bri;ht, r p. of the greens, and the floor will look lake mahogany, and. have a fine (ma.
dean Win'e mt.
Let a board be fixed in the wirndow,;and one 'Ago* p„ laced upon it within a.nd another w out; in ordet,~ifit" know that they are clean, let them be fled rubbed with a, thick damp clothe aacl then )with ^ilty one ; if any fp~oots, remain, put upg1r. 4mrfpnae w Awn, rub t n',t. clean, and they will have a tram' acct s earanee:
~. cleax kl-rloasbl laid t.,,J,Jqrea
I,qt;,tlteni be	rubbed every,4ay,	once a w Iv e.0 lc tn{ , upfide d.nwn., fax. a Y 4104. .at Bird, t e:yc r let. the .be rubest ap t andlhu. out to dry, then let them be robbed over wit a c and they will look as well as at firit.
D4eai fns t, w4 Lace-

Rub your lace over with loft foil), then	.it, O F
fmooth board, upon which. apiece of cloth a been fait' Viewed ; put over it another piece of cloth, and let
it,be puk into a bs d ‘v 'oh dean water and kept on the fire till it is. fc- Ins hot., : Then le it out and firetch the lace on a board ; rub it with, a hard b`rulh to-take out the foapt,° t, r,ptt,it-ag -again intp boiling water,.. and keep preing14 vkgtl; a brullt tall y.ou ~et-trl~ dirt
wl}olely gut.	yank, t.41.1k it ciea~a, u}ix f4 ne kluy
with clean water and let it boil,, aftez which malge fp good ilarch, and put t4 at ;, giyq, it a geu~tle,;bs~tl ,a lqueeze it out. Then hang the board with the lace up, to dry, and take it off.. When the lace is taken off,., 1etit be put between two fheetsof paper,- aweightlaid
w
•
rge ¶P t: 'r A 1~'1 inL x! 1( s t A I C T 4rff. over it all ig'ht,. at;din the' morning it Will' 'hook is
freth as who ,new.
To ntaki Lear thatk it turned ffellien) . a4)e4r' iw It .
Mix 'a'qquarter of an• ounce of po led' blue, with "a-quarter of a . , `nd 'of Aft 'foap,` rub' it'b''~e ( the lacer and put it' in . .the water while it told ; if it is very yellow, it will require three boilings, but if not"tw l will be fufficient. When you take it out, rub it over. with foap and blue mixed as before, then let it hang up to dry in the fun, after which ` you muff Wit it again,. xrtd it. will. be as..white•aa if new.
routwiz' C~rmarie '
When you have loaded therntvetl,let than be waffled in warm water, then mix tome foal; aitd Mee together and rub it on the cloaths, then lay them in a tub, and. pour boiling water upon them ; When they have laid two hours in the water, wafh them out, and letthem lie rinfed in cold pump water with blues Take great care how you-iron them, otherwifb they will" be apt• to finge..
ro zvafh Pbread and Cotton Stocking:.
Let them be well lathered twice, and once boiled in' water mixed with blue; then lest them be wanted` out and folded up without rinfing; put a weight upon them, and let them be preffed at leaft half an hour, then hang them up to dry ; let them be rolled' without ironing, and they will look as wLll•as ifs new.
2'o zuafli' 1~'0. fred'SYocfingr
Let them be waffled in a cool lather till they are quite clean, but no leap mutt be put to them, only let them be rinfed out in cold water; and hung up to dry, fold them and they will' be fir for,'u'e.	•
Te avi fh fine Mufrnt
When you. have.folded.uT the muffins, let them-he Eut. into clean. water that ts, not very hot,. otherwife. they;
'!MiO ''F'*$44 4141 7 Mgt' Ott *fa w	'' the	"
R..y	l 'F..F. •	1
MA.
r r.	rune	oug a ne c +	•it<< : ;~
/af fine foap, by beating it wi a fm. .'	c turn Ri
round; but take care that it has pto,Wli	hen
let the munsbe.put intp the water, ax	cue
by one, and laid t;p foak an water till th ''	s	r
out Tile ; them in dater tnalk warm, aaa
therxt,out a~	Cl as ofhble, lef an
' part of
t ouh retatn.an. ~V hen, y''make' u ,.tke their out, ay them into an earthen dills,' and a lather Like the flea only the water mutt be more hot, but not boiling, otherwife it will be apt to injure their ; mix Ionic ater. with powder blue, and pour it to the hot water, taking care to keep it ffirrin until.the_wbole begins to have a blui,th ,colour. 'Talct em s .try fiat}~ viien . yp.a have

.11144e...a lather in the . f am  ;natfu r4 thelTaft' put .the
t} ufirys,into,it, and c o v e r - with adean cloth; yt. &heln lie in that lather till ~moroutg, thep ,put theta .i4.to,col4 water and wafh out the ftlap.
I a rixce 1ktss b fore tbcj+ ,are flarcbed.
Tape a little pump water, and mix it with fume pow-
'.der blue, fhake the whole together, and then put to it .a little more,pump water fqueeze the muilint through ic,; one at a.tt ng, otherwife,it will make the ' ,appear yellow. Rub'them gently with your hand in the water., left any remains of the blue should fettle in them;'ttut if they,appeax ytie llpw~you must pat more blue to them. When you ave riijteii' them la cold wateWater *let thgst, be prelled as hand as poflible, for unlefs the is quite out ,they will not take.the ftarch; then let them be pul-Jed out and laid on a dry cloth.
, . a arch Mu 'rrt.
.Put a'pint of puanpwater into a clean skillet, and
mix with It a quarter of n pout}d of flare ; keep it over
a flow fire• until at is Luke warm but take care to ftir it
till it begins to boil,, Chet,} )et, ids ae .talyen off, and when
it has gofi a tptpt} , our.iyt Into a clear earthen dial ;
cover it over y ttl' a.4+elf plate all it is cold, theta, pu)t
to
i
'fx A ILY INSTRIMT
to It a little blue ; Make your muffins, atid	gild t
out' fa esterrtic ivetI the gtrch, taking care that k be ,iW:t too. thick. Lay the March firll over oars !'ir3e and the* the other, and that which has been *fed for the fine muffins, .will °do well enough'for tilde et-are cosirfer. When you have ftarched them, let the* be Iaid iiitoa clean earthen dirk, aud keep prang them of the starch begins to flick to your hands ; then wring it out of Them with a clean Both, and rub them till they 'are dry.

e clap Mu/ins before.
When yon have opened them, rub them through your hands, then keep clapping them together till they ' are hard, but if you find any wet or hatch on your hands, want them, and keep them as dry as feiiible, pthe'rwife the mullins will never look well. Pull them both ways with your hands, becaufe that prevents the muffin from fraying, and when they are quite drys fpread them out and hold them between you and the light by which you will fee whether any of the starch remains in them, and if it does, you muff rub it again in your hands. If there is any of the ftarch in them you will fee it thine, but if not they will fly a fender when clapped. Take care to 'dap them tingly, otherwife they will be apt to fray and tear.

The bell Method of ironing Muflint.
When you have wafhed your hands very clean, after clapping the muffins, let the cloaths be pulled out double on a very fmooth board, laying at lea4t five or fix on each other. When you have heated your iron, put it into the box, when you mutt let it remain till the heat, is full through it ; then take the piece of muffin that lies lowelt, becaufe it will be more dry than the others, by which method they will all fhcceec each other in k regular order, and look extremely fine. If the muflins are fine they muff be done on a very Loft woolen cloth", but thole that are coarfe may be done on one that is more damp, or the under fide of that firit°ufed.
LTags FAM IL'1 INI.TR,tJC'T;OR. 193
The bs/t fife bsa- •f f afebiv' <jul~i ol*s.
Th mutt be wa flied a*l fielafitd 1 IA#Me` manner as muffins, and the ftarch muff be as'thria.itt-xobl+e. Dip them gently into it, then let them be taken out and fqueezed through *ben +hands ,ahtil the water is forced out, then dry them, with a fine cloth; clap them withgreat`care, otherwife, you will be apt to damage them, and when you have folded them up, let them be put into a clean pan, but let no wet come near them, otherwife it will give them a yellowifh colour: Let them be ironed on a clean fmooth woolen cloth, but take care that the iron be not too hot, and the ftafch mutt be made for the purpofe, for that ufed for muflms will not do..

l`o rwafh Blond Lace and Gauzes.
Let them be wafhed in three differentwaters, each of which mull be well lathered, and tolerable warm, then let them be tinted in water mixed with blue, and ht;ng up to dry, then ftarch them and hang them up a-
gain. Take three pints of water, and put in it half a pound of ifinglafs; let it boil till it is reduced to one pint ; then dip the gauze into it, and when you have fqueezedl it out let it be properly flarched and bleed, always taking care to iron them as loon afterwards as you can, which will make them look much better.


T'he heft Method of making and"ufing Starch.
Moisten the q.u.aiitilly of March you want to life, ac-cording to the quantity of your cloaths, with water, and put as much hone blue as is necefiary. When the (larch and blue are. properly mixed, then let the whole boil together a quarter of an hour longer, taking care to keep ftirring it, becaufe that makes it much Iliffer and is better for the linen. Such things as you would have molt stiff, ought to be put firit into the water, and you may weaken the ftarch by pouring a litttle water upon it. Starch ought to be boiled in a
copper vefl'el, becaufe it requires much boiling, and tin is apt to make it burn, Some people mix their S	Rarer
.
t'
rg~	F tI 11Y r I RS trR`T
''larch with ,llom, or gum terabits, nothiage is fo good as ifinglafs, aid an ou+ a of it fafficient to :a• gttattter of a pooled.
TO clean Gold and ,Silver Lactic
Rub the crumb of a f}aie theeg-pFnnty loaf between your hands till it is very fine, then mix, it wjth a, gear-ter of an ounce of powder blue; lay it upon the Jace, and rub it with your hands till it begins to appear btight; then take a piece of thin flannel to duff off what remains of the crumbs; and lastly rub it with a piece of crimton velvet, and it will look as well as at firm.,

d'o preferve Golder Silver Lace from tarxifhreg,
Gold orfilver lace mull never be put into adeal box, becaufe that is lure of proving huetfal to it; but when it has been ufed let it be put up in indian paper, and wrap other paper round it; then take a piece of green baize, and when it is well aired before the fire, lap it round the paper and put it into a trunk, the paper of which ought to be well Rained with faffron.

To take Spots out of woolen Cloth.
Take fome of the bell fullers earth that can be got ; then lay it before the fire till it is quite hard, and beat it in a morter till it is as fine as powder, then mix with it a fufficient quantity of oil of turpentine, and make it up in balls, which you may keep betide you and ufe in the following manner. Put one of them into a path filled with boiling water, and when it is diffolved let it he laid on the fpots, where it muff. remain till it is dry
then rub it with a hard brufh till all the fpots are out, when you mull take a piece of thin cloth and rub over. it to take out what remains of the fullers earth.

re clean Ribl aids
When you have fprinkled them with clean water, let
then be smoothed out, then lay them at full length on
a carpet till you make a lather of Cathie foap, then rub
them gently over with a brufh, or foft woolen cloth.
Mix
-	OArMlt'li- IN94	t 'If tai It Ng-
Mix ,fome valet wat`aM •aad' wltit'tt'ar', and- rum them well in it.. ISl yott ibikreee thitr itt4thid *fey wilt not only be clean,. but the colour will #Fc pteferved from fading, and you mutt dry them ilea shady place...
take Spots of ik or t he out o, j,` Clot/ or Linen.
Rub the juice of lemon. On the fpots, as hen it dryletit be wafhed in warm water. If oudofotwice, the (pots `will difappear, in cloth, but if~it is linen, put fcente bo'ihh'g water into a pewter pot,. hold that part. that has the fpot, tight together over the Ream, then rub it with" the juice of lemon,, and the Bets wild; difaphpear.
TO keep Silk from 'Paining irewa,thing:.
. Fill ,a fence pan with water,; and let it fiend on the' fire till it is partly hot, them difl'olve. in it a proper quantity of Catlile foap, then take it off the fire and when it is almoft cold, put to it handful of fullers, earth, and fcour your filk with it. Be fore to let them... be fpread out, for if they are laid in.heaps together,. it will fpoil them.

To keep Linezrnot' of d, from receiving any Damage.
When it is washed and well dried, fold it up in the neatell manner, fcattee between each of the foldings: powder of cedar wood ; and let the trunk, drawer, or box, be perfumed With - thorax..
To take Spots out.ef Boards or ltzrge rabies.
Make fome lye of wood afhes, and put in it a few galls, then lay it on the fpots, and let it lie on them one night, in the morning rub the boards or tables with a hard bruth, but if it is on the floor you,do it on your knees. Take care You rob it with the rain,, and at the fecond fcotiring, put ouit sehAndful. of aeifend, and rub it over with a wdelen cloth rllTnnneof the fpots can be feat. When y'eu have brought thereto a fine tranf-
parent
40
to THE' RAMILY INSTRkCFCT€ft:
parent colour, let them be waffled with cold water,. for if done with hot water, it opens the grain,. and, fpoile their appearance..

TO clean old Ph7ures witbout;damaging the Paintings..
Take a quarte'of 4n ounce of roman vitriol, and two, ounces of prax; beat them together very fmall, then let them ~filled through a fine lawn fieve ; and when. you have rubbed the duff off the piture,, lay it flat on. the ground, and throw force of powder over it, then dip a broth in clean water, and rub it over the canvas. until the painting begins to appear as if new, you muff not take any more water than will jun. wet the powder,. and when the pi&ure appears to be clean,, and all the duff is rubbed off, fet it up to dry in a place not too much expofed to the fun. Then take-a little linfeed oi.l,. dip a feather in it and rub it gently over.. the picture,, bat aunt let the oil dry off too foon, for the longer it is kept moift the more tranfparent will the colour appear.
T 'o clean the Frames of Piaurss.
Wadi off the dirt, with cold water, make a Long, fjap lather and rub them with a fpunge dipped in it, till they are clean, then fet them in the air to dry, and nub: them bright with a woolen cloth..
F 1 N 1 S.
4,	j`	s.	•
— s	(
r-	n
