<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt n=" A Contemplation of Bassetts-down-Hill">
            <title>A Contemplation of Bassetts down-Hill</title>
            <author n="Kemp, Anne">Kemp, Anne</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to
the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided 
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact
either: Women Writers Resource Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic
collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>1996</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Women Writers Resource Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Kemp, Anne.  A Contemplation of Bassetts-down-Hill. Oxford, 1658. Broadside. EEB 1151:12</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is produced in conjunction with the 
Women Writers Resource Project at Emory University</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <rs type="ethnicity">Caucasian</rs>
            <rs type="form">unedited</rs>
            <rs type="genre">prose</rs>
            <rs type="geography">Great Britain</rs>
            <date>1600-1699</date>
         </creation>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1997</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Scott Ellis</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="kemp.001" n=" A Contemplation of Bassetts-down-Hill" type="">
            <docAuthor>Kemp, Anne. </docAuthor>
            <head>
               <title> A Contemplation of Bassetts-down-Hill</title>
            </head>
            <docDate> 1658</docDate>
            <argument>
               <p>Poem describing a rural setting, perhaps in Gloucester.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>A Contemplation on Bassets-down-Hill by the most Sacred adorer of the Muses<lb/>
Mrs A. K.</p>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>If that exact Appelles now did live.</l>
               <l>And would a picture of Elizium give;</l>
               <l>He might pourtrai' of the prospect which this Hill</l>
               <l>Doth shew; &amp; make the eie command at will.</l>
               <l>Heer's many a shire whose pleasauntness for fight</l>
               <l>Doth yield to the Spectators great delight.</l>
               <l>Ther's a large Field guilded with ceres gold;</l>
               <l>Here a green mead doth many Heifers hold;</l>
               <l>Ther's pasture growne with virdant grass, whose store,</l>
               <l>Of Argent-sheep shewes th'owner is not poore.</l>
               <l>Here springs doe intricate Meanders make</l>
               <l>Excelling farr Oblivion's Lethe Lake.</l>
               <l>There woods and Coppisses harbour as many</l>
               <l>And sweet melodious Choristers, as any</l>
               <l>Elizium yields; whose Philomel' an lazes</l>
               <l>Merit the highest of the Lyrick's praise</l>
               <l>Heer's Flora deck't with robes of Or, and Azur,</l>
               <l>Fragrently smelling yield's two senses pleasure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
               <l>Hence Zephirus doth breath his gentle gales</l>
               <l>Coole on the Hills, and sweet throughout the Vales</l>
               <l>How happy are they that in this Climate dwell?</l>
               <l>Alas! they can't their owne sweet welfare tell;</l>
               <l>Scarce I my selfe whil'st I am here doe know it</l>
               <l>Till I fee it's Antithesis to shew it.</l>
               <l>Here are no smoaking streets, nor howling cryes,</l>
               <l>Deafning the eares, nor blinding of the eyes;</l>
               <l>No noysome smells t' infect, and choake the aire;</l>
               <l>breeding diseases envious to the Faire.</l>
               <l>Deceipt is here exil'd from Flesh, and Bloud:</l>
               <l> (Strife only reigns, for all strive to be good.)</l>
               <l>With Will his verse I here will make an end</l>
               <l>And as the crab doth alwaies backward bend</l>
               <l>So, though from this sweet place I goe away</l>
               <l>My loyall heart will in this Climate stay.</l>
               <l>Thus heartless, doth my worthless body rest</l>
               <l>Whilest my heart liveth with the ever blest.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>