The New Star
1
I was musing in the twilight of a bright and 
beauteous land.
Of its lovely streams, its placid lakes, and 
hoary mountains grand.
Twas strewn with flowers of every hue and 
bore upon its breast – 
A gem whose brightness far exceeds the purest 
diamond crest.
2
There was beauty in its valleys, in its fountains 
and its rills,
And happiness with viewless touch awaked 
to joy its hills,
There was beauty in its banner as it gracefully 
unfurled,
Its triple folds in triumph o’er and all
admiring world.
3
With blessings heaven crowned it – all was beauty, 
peace and love,
The angles smiled upon it from the star-gemmed 
vault above,
A thrill of joy rushed o’er my soul, those
foaming ??? grand - 
And those mighty streams were sparkling in
my own, my native land!
4
Then the shadowy veil of night came down
 and oh, what darkness drear
Fell on my beauteous visions so lately filled with cheer,
In agony I wildly wept – all happiness 
had fled,
And before me was a bloody pall, where 
Peace lay cold and dead!
5
What maniac horde had thither rushed, 
what demon of the air,
What fiery brand and withering breath had 
wrought the ruin there?
Who barred the glorious sunlight from those 
sweet Magnolia bowers
And sprinkled human blood upon those 
fairy fruits and flowers?
6
Columbia! My native land, Oh, where is 
now thy boast.
The united hope and destiny of thy 
freedom-loving host?
Thy glory has departed, and a guilty
 erring one 
With brother’s blood would desecrate the home 
of Washington.
7
The night is black around thee – will it
ne’er be light again,
Will the crimson blood like rivers flow
upon each sunny plain?
Alas! the temple is devided, then why 
should canon roar,
Their thundering tones but echo “we’re
parted evermore”!

Come, sacred Peace, above us, for we
never more can be,
United with the tyrants, who would 
Subjugate the free,
8
Yes, the veil is rend asunder! See how 
human passions swell
For every thundering echo is a solemn
Funeral Knell 
Oh, God in pity hear us! Send a message 
of Peace
To quell the roaring ???? and their mighty
????curse.
9
In comparison came this answer, On
The ruins there a ray
Bringing to the worn and weary ???
of a brighter day
All honor to the nation born – the beautiful
New Star
That gleams above oppression like an angel 
from afar.
Star of the South! Where e’er I gaze thy
radiant light is there
And ‘neath its ray my spirit kneels in 
gratitude and prayer
Shine on through endless ages o’er the field
by heroes trod
that lead each Southern patriot onto glory and to God

Extra
All honor to the nation born, the beautiful 
new star,
that gleams above oppressiuon like an angel
from afar.

Star of the South! Where e’er I gaze
thy peaceful light is there,
And ‘neath its ray a nation bows in 
gratitude and prayer,
Shine on, through endless ages, o’er the fields by heroes trod
And light each noble patriot to glory and 
to God!
