“THE SOLDIERS’ VICTORY OF FAITH
This is the victory that hath overcome the world. – John 5th-4.
(By Mrs. Loula Kendall Rogers, State Poet Laureate U.D.C., for the Annual Convention in Moutrie, October, 1929)
Aurora gleamed in beauty o’er the hills,
And cast a ray of golden charm that thrills
A soldier lone, who wandered ‘neath the dome
of Mountain’s sheltering arm o’er sun-lit home.
Admiringly he gazed upon the view,
The kneeling there where woodland flowers grew,
He plead for Heavenly guidance on his way,
For he must meet impending battle on that day!

‘Twas thus at Valley Forge the Washington
Invoked the mighty “King of Kings,” and won!
For never a warrior in other lands had brought
So great a victory as he in Faith has wrought
Our vast Republic that extends from sea to sea,
Whose banners wave in triumph o’er the Free;
For Heaven has spread great blessings on our land,
Of Peace and Plenty by Divine command.
Years pass – Then o’er the plains of Mexico
Near by the gates of Alamo,
The thundering sound of guns proclaim
That United States have won the fame,
For Marion in his War-time creed,
And Zachary Taylor proved help in need,
While Jefferson Davis in that Mexican War,
Was at Buena Vista a reigning Star!

A proof that undying Faith was there,
For our bravest leaders won by prayer;
Not one private home did they efface,
Nor cruelly burn a Court House place;
This Law kept General Lee for years
As he spared in mercy a widow’s tears,
And by all nations his Orders were known,
For his memory is reverenced by the world is shown.

Who can forget brave Stonewall Jackson
Whose Living Faith illumed each action?
And Bishop Polk near Kennesaw’s height
Who was visually crowned in Immortal Light?
Later on the same true faith abides,
As Pershing the honored Chieftian guides,
While Victory crowns with success anew,
And all nations admire his allegiance true.

Then Hail!  All Hail!  With thankful voice acclaim,
That Victory Above, crowns the true soldier with fame!
Let Earth and Heaven rejoice on land and sea afar
When Faith and Love combined have won the brightest
Star!
